<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<lgr xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:lgr-1.0">
  <meta>
    <version comment="Root Zone LGR for the Malayalam Script">5</version>
    <date>2022-05-26</date>
    <language>und-Mlym</language>
    <scope type="domain">.</scope>
    <unicode-version>11.0.0</unicode-version>
    <description type="text/html"><![CDATA[
    
    <h1>Root Zone Label Generation Rules for the Malayalam script</h1>
    
    <h2>Overview</h2>    
    <p>This file contains Label Generation Rules (LGR) for the Malayalam script for the Root Zone. 
     For details on the development of this LGR and additional background on the script, 
     see “Proposal for a Malayalam Script Root Zone Label Generation 
     Ruleset (LGR)” [Proposal-Malayalam]. 
     This file is one of a set of LGR files that together form an integrated LGR for the DNS Root Zone [RZ-LGR-5]. 
     The format of this file follows [RFC 7940].</p>

    <h2>Repertoire</h2>
    <p>The repertoire contains 70 code points for letters used in the Malayalam language
    in addition to 11 sequences used in defining variants, bringing the total repertoire entries to 81.</p>

    <p>For more detail, see Section 5, “Repertoire” in [Proposal-Malayalam].</p>

    <p>The repertoire is based on [MSR-5], which is a subset of [Unicode 11.0].</p>

    <p>As part of the Root Zone, this LGR includes neither decimal digits nor the HYPHEN-MINUS.</p>
      
     <p>Code points outside the Malayalam script that are listed in this file are targets
       for out-of-script variants and are identified by a reflexive (identity)
       variant of type “out-of-repertoire-var”. They do not form part of the
       repertoire.</p>

    <p>Each code point is tagged with the script or scripts with which the code point is used, one or more other character categories,
    and one or more references documenting sufficient justification for inclusion in the repertoire; see “References” below.</p>

   <h2>Variants</h2>
    <p>This LGR defines in-script variants and cross-script variants as described in Section 6, “Variants”, in [Proposal-Malayalam].
    One in-script variant is due to the multiple ways to write the conjunct 
    “nta” in Malayalam.  Cross-script variants for related scripts are mainly defined for Tamil code points, as well as for Oriya and Myanmar.</p>

    <p>For consistency with other RZ-LGRs, cross-script variants to ASCII code points are listed explicitly as well. For the Malayalam
    LGR this requires the addition of one redundant sequence U+0D1F U+0D1F. This sequence has no effect on available labels.</p>
    
    <p><b>Variant Disposition:</b> All variants are of type “blocked”, making labels that differ only by these variants mutually exclusive:  
    whichever label containing either of these variants is chosen earlier, the other one equivalent variant label should be blocked. 
    There is no preference among these variants.</p>

    <p>This LGR does not define allocatable variants.</p>

    <p><b>Additional Variants:</b> This LGR inherits additional blocked cross-script variants by integration; they may not be listed here unless they result in
    in-script variants. See the merged, Common LGR [RZ-LGR-5] for details of all applicable cross-script variants,
    including any not listed here; always use the Common LGR for determining cross-script collisions of labels.</p>

    <p>The specification of variants in the Root Zone LGR follows the guidelines in [RFC 8228].</p>

    <p><b>Context Rules for Variants:</b> some of the variants defined in this LGR are “effective null variants”, that is,
    some code points in the source map to “nothing” in the target with all other code points unchanged.
    (Because mappings are symmetric, it does not matter whether it is the forward or reverse mapping that
    maps to “null” ). Such variants require a context rule to keep the variant set well-behaved. Symmetry requires
    the same context rule for both forward and reverse mappings.</p>
   
    <p>In other cases, the sequences or code points making up source and target are constrained by context
    rules on the code points. In such a case, any variants require context rules that match the intersection
    between the contexts for both source and target; otherwise a sequence might be considered valid in some
    variant label when it would not be valid in an equivalent context in an original label.</p>

    <h2>Character Classes</h2>
    <p>The basic characters in Malayalam are classified here into the following categories: Consonants, Vowels, 
    Matra and Reordrant Vowel Diacritics, Halant, Visarga, Anusvara and Chillu letters. </p>
    
    <p><b>Consonant:</b> Malayalam is written in an abugida script derived ultimately from Brahmi in which 
    every consonant carries an inherent /a/. More details in Section 3.8, “The Structure of 
    Malayalam Script” of [Proposal-Malayalam].</p>
    
    <p><b>Vowels:</b> Like consonants, the independent vowels can follow any other class of code points in a label.</p>

    <p><b>Matra:</b> Vowels other than the inherent vowel are written as vowel diacritics. They are referred to as Matras, 
    when they follow consonants. More details in Section 3.8, “The Structure of Malayalam Script” of [Proposal-Malayalam].</p>
    
    <p><b>Halant:</b> A consonant can be combined with another consonant or conjunct 
    using the halant encoded as U+0D4D MALAYALAM SIGN VIRAMA. This strips off the implicit vowel. 
     More details in Section 3.8, “The Structure of Malayalam Script” of [Proposal-Malayalam].</p>

    <p><b>Anusvara:</b> In Malayalam, anusvara represented as U+0D02, simply represents a consonant /m/ after a vowel, 
    though this /m/ may be assimilated to another nasal consonant. More details in Section 3.8, “The Structure of Malayalam 
    Script” of [Proposal-Malayalam].</p>

    <p><b>Visarga:</b> The visarga represents a consonant /h/ after a vowel, 
    and is transliterated as ḥ. Like the anusvara, it is a special symbol, and is never followed by an 
    inherent vowel or another vowel. More details in Section 3.8, “The Structure of Malayalam 
    Script” of [Proposal-Malayalam].</p>

    <p><b>Chillu:</b> Chillu letters, aka “Chillaksharam”, represent pure consonants without any vowel sound. 
    More details in Section 3.8, “The Structure of Malayalam Script” of [Proposal-Malayalam].</p>
    
    <p><b>Reordrant:</b> Vowel diacritics, part of which reorder around the preceding character or conjunct. 
    More details in Sections 6.1 “In-script Variants” and 7.1.1 “Variables or definitions” of [Proposal-Malayalam].</p>    
        
    <h2>Whole Label Evaluation (WLE) and Context Rules</h2>
   <h3>Default Whole Label Evaluation Rules and Actions</h3>
   <p>The LGR includes the set of required default WLE rules and actions applicable to 
    the Root Zone and defined in [MSR-5]. They are marked with &#x235F;. The 
    default prohibition on leading combining marks is equivalent to ensuring that 
    a label only starts with a consonant or vowel.</p>
    
    <h3>Malayalam-specific Rules</h3>
    <p>There are constraints on the context for many of the character classes in Malayalam. 
    A corresponding set of context and whole label rules has been formulated for LGR specification, as described in
    Section 7, “Whole Label Evaluation (WLE) Rules” in [Proposal-Malayalam].</p>
    
    <p>The following symbols are used in the WLE rules: 
    <br/>C    →    Consonant
    <br/>M    →    Matra
    <br/>V    →    Vowel
    <br/>B    →    Anusvara
    <br/>X    →    Visarga 
    <br/>D    →    Chandrabindu
    <br/>H    →    Halant
    <br/>L    →    Chillu
    <br/>R    →    Reordrant Matra
    </p>
    <p><b>Note:</b> the Reordrant Matras include one sequence. That requires an auxiliary rule R in addition to class R.</p>
    
    <p>The rules are: </p>
    <ul>
        <li>1. H: must be preceded by C or U+0D41</li>
        <li>2. M: must be preceded by C</li>
        <li>3. B: must be preceded by C, V or M</li>
        <li>4. X: must be preceded by C, V or M</li>
        <li>5. L: cannot be preceded by B, X or H</li>
        <li>6. A label does not begin with L</li> 
    </ul>
    <p>The following context rules apply to Consonants U+0D33 LLA and U+0D31 RRA as well as to sequences ending in these code points:</p>
    <ul>
      <li>7. The character U+0D33 cannot immediately follow U+0D33, except as part of a defined sequence</li>
      <li>8. The character U+0D31 cannot immediately follow U+0D31, except as part of a defined sequence</li>
    </ul>
    <p><b>Note:</b> the implementation of Rules 7 &amp; 8 relies on the fact that a context rule is not evaluated between code points in the same sequence. 
    For example, if a label contains two adjacent U+0D33 U+0D33 surrounded by other code points , the two code points can only be interpreted 
    as the sequence U+0D33 U+0D33 because a singleton U+0D33 is not allowed to be followed by another U+0D33.
    </p>
    <p>The following context rule applies to the sequence Chillu N + Halant (U+0D7B U+0D4D):</p>
    <ul>
      <li>9. The sequence U+0D7B U+0D4D must be preceded by C, L, M, V and must be followed by U+0D31</li>
    </ul>
    
    <h3>Context rules for Variants</h3>
    <p>The following context rules apply to variants:</p>
    <ul>
        <li>V1: A variant is defined when followed by U+0D31</li>
        <li>V2: A variant preceded by 0D33+Halant or followed by R or Halant+0D33 is not defined</li>
        <li>V3: A variant preceded by 0D31+Halant or followed by R or Halant+0D31 is not defined</li>
    </ul>
    
    <p>These rules ensure that the variant label sets are well-behaved in cases where variant sequences overlap.</p>

    <p><b>Note:</b> any sequences ending with 0D31 would overlap with the various variant sequences beginning with 0D31, therefore this
    LGR drops the 0D31 from the end of these sequences, but adds context rule V1, when="followed-by-0D31" instead. Because all the variants
    also end in 0D31, this results in the same generated variants as if the sequences had been defined with trailing U+0D31, but now the 
    variants are well-behaved in all contexts.</p>

    <p>More details in Section 6.1, “In-script Variants” and Section 7, “Whole Label Evaluation Rules (WLE)” of [Proposal-Malayalam]</p>

    <p>There are a number of cross-script homoglyphs to U+0D31 RRA, which would interact with the definition of in-script sequences and 
    variants, leading to unacceptable complexity. These variants would affect only labels made solely of letters
    RRA, and no other labels. Rule 8 already restricts labels consisting solely of copies of the letter RRA to either “റ” or “ററ”, thus 
    allowing only two such labels. The following rule disallows the remaining two possible labels, obviating any need to define these
    cross-script variants.</p>
    
    <ul>
        <li>10. A label cannot consist solely of letters U+0D31 RRA</li>
    </ul>

    <h3>Malayalam-specific actions</h3>
    <p>WLE rules 6 and 10 trigger Malayalam-specific actions to invalidate any original and variant labels not satisfying the constraints. 
    See Section 7, “Whole Label Evaluation (WLE) Rules” in [Proposal-Malayalam].</p>

    <h2>Methodology and Contributors</h2>
     <p>The Root Zone LGR for the Malayalam script was developed by the Neo-Brahmi Generation Panel (NBGP) the members of which have experience in
     linguistics and computational linguistics in a wide variety of languages written with Neo-Brahmi scripts. Under the Neo-Brahmi Generation 
     Panel, there are nine scripts belonging to separate Unicode blocks. Each of these scripts has been assigned a separate LGR, with the 
     Neo-Brahmi GP ensuring that the fundamental philosophy behind building each LGR is in sync with all other Brahmi-derived scripts. For 
     further details on methodology and contributors, see Sections 4 and 8 in [Proposal-Malayalam], as well as [RZ-LGR-5-Overview].</p>

     <h3>Changes from LGR-3</h3>

     <p>This LGR has been updated for LGR-4 to address an inconsistency involving the conjunct “nta” and to eliminate some potentially complex 
     interactions with cross-script variants. For the prior version see [RZ-LGR-3-Mlym].</p> 

     <ol>
     <li>
     <p>Removed Chillu N from rule 1 and added a new context rule applied to the sequence Chillu N + Halant (U+0D7B U+0D4D):</p>
     <ul>
      <li>9. The sequence U+0D7B U+0D4D must be preceded by C, L, M, V and must be followed by U+0D31</li>
     </ul>
     <p>This change disallows some contexts that should not have been allowed for U+0D4D when following U+0D7B.</p>
     </li>
     <li>
     <p>Added a new context rule applied to variants:</p>
     <ul>
       <li>V1: A variant is defined when followed by U+0D31</li>
     </ul>
     <p>The definition of the sequences to which this context rule applies has been changed by dropping the final U+0D31. 
     This is an equivalent formulation. The change simplifies the formulation of other rules and variant definitions.</p>
     </li>
     <li>
      <p>Added a new whole-label rule (and corresponding action):</p>
      <ul>
         <li>10. A label cannot consist solely of letters U+0D31 RRA</li>
     </ul>
     <p>This rule invalidates the two labels U+0D31 and U+0D31 U+0D31, obviating the need to define certain cross-script variants for U+0D31</p>
     </li>
     </ol>
     <p>Note: as result of the update, the LGR is slightly more restrictive.</p>
     
    <h3>Changes from LGR-4</h3>

    <p>As result of integration with additional scripts, this LGR has been updated. This update does not change the set of labels available
    under this LGR. For the prior version see [RZ-LGR-4-Mlym].</p>
    
    <p>Integration with scripts newly added to LGR-5 adds cross-script variants to ASCII code points, such as between U+00^F and U+0D20, or 
    between U+0073 and U+0D1F. For the latter, the Latin LGR [RZ-LGR-Latin] also
    declares an in-script variant between U+0073 U+0073 and U+00DF, requiring the definition of a sequence U+0073 U+0073. Therefore the sequence 
    U+0073 U+0073 automatically inherits a variant to any sequence U+0D1F U+0D1F occurring in a Malayalam label. Transitivity of variants on the 
    code point level requires explicit declaration of a sequence U+0D1F U+0D1F. Except for the purposes of allowing a variant, that sequence 
    would not need to be defined in the Malayalam LGR because it is redundant: the LGR already supports the repetition of the singleton code point
    U+0D1F without restriction.</p> 

    <p>Even though cross-script variants with the Latin or other scripts with cross-script variants to U+0D1F are not otherwise listed in this LGR, 
    the sequence U+0D1F U+0D1F has been added here exceptionally, as have the variants between U+0073 and U+0D1F. Doing so ensures that the sequence 
    forms part of the merged repertoire in Common LGR [RZ-LGR-5] and that any cross-script variants defined for it can be computed using 
    that LGR. Being redundant other than in the definition of variants, adding the sequence does not change the labels available under this LGR.</p>

    <p>Note that the listing of variants for U+0D1F and U+0D1F U+0D1F in this LGR is that minimally required for integration. Additional cross-script 
    variants for these repertoire elements exist and are defined in [RZ-LGR-5].For consistency across RZ-LGRs, imposed variants to ASCII
    code points and to the Myanmar script are now explicitly listed as well</p>.

    <h2>References</h2> 
    <p>The following general references are cited in this document:</p>
    <dl class="references">
    <dt>[MSR-5]</dt>
    <dd>Integration Panel, “Maximal Starting Repertoire — MSR-5 Overview and Rationale”, 24 June 2021, 
    https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/msr-5-overview-24jun21-en.pdf</dd> 

    <dt>[Proposal-Malayalam]</dt> 
    <dd>Neo-Brahmi Generation Panel, “Proposal for a Malayalam Script Root Zone Label Generation Ruleset (LGR)”, Updated 26 June 2020, https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/proposal-malayalam-lgr-26jun20-en.pdf</dd>

    <dt>[RFC 7940]</dt>
    <dd>Davies, K. and A. Freytag, “Representing Label Generation Rulesets Using XML”, RFC 7940, August 2016, https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7940</dd> 
     
    <dt>[RFC 8228]</dt>
    <dd>A. Freytag, “Guidance on Designing Label Generation Rulesets (LGRs) Supporting Variant Labels”, RFC 8228, August 2017,
    https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8228</dd>

    <dt>[RZ-LGR-5]</dt>
    <dd>Integration Panel, “Root Zone Label Generation Rules (RZ-LGR-5)”, 26 May 2022 (XML), https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/rz-lgr-5-common-26may22-en.xml <br/>
    <i>non-normative HTML presentation: https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/rz-lgr-5-common-26may22-en.html</i></dd>

    <dt>[RZ-LGR-3-Mlym]</dt>
    <dd>ICANN, Root Zone Label Generation Rules for the Malayalam Script (und-Mlym), Version 3, 10 July 2019 (XML)
    https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/lgr-3-malayalam-script-10jul19-en.xml <br/>
    <i>non-normative HTML presentation: https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/lgr-3-malayalam-script-10jul19-en.html</i></dd>

    <dt>[RZ-LGR-4-Mlym]</dt>
    <dd>ICANN, Root Zone Label Generation Rules for the Malayalam Script (und-Mlym), Version 4, 5 November 2020 (XML)
    https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/lgr-4-malayalam-script-05nov20-en.xml <br/>
    <i>non-normative HTML presentation: https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/lgr-4-malayalam-script-05nov20-en.html</i></dd>

    <dt>[RZ-LGR-Latin]</dt>
    <dd>“Root Zone Label Generation Rules for the Latin Script”, 26 May 2022, https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/rz-lgr-5-latin-script-26may22-en.xml <br/>
    <i>non-normative HTML presentation: https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/rz-lgr-5-latin-script-26may22-en.html</i></dd>

    <dt>[RZ-LGR-5-Overview]</dt>
    <dd>Integration Panel, “Root Zone Label Generation Rules (RZ LGR-5): Overview and Summary”, 26 May 2022, https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/rz-lgr-5-overview-26may22-en.pdf</dd>

    <dt>[Unicode 11.0]</dt>
    <dd>The Unicode Consortium. The Unicode Standard, Version 11.0.0, (Mountain View, CA: The Unicode Consortium, 2018. ISBN 978-1-936213-19-1) 
     https://www.unicode.org/versions/Unicode11.0.0/</dd>
     </dl>
      <p>For references consulted particularly in designing the repertoire for the Malayalam script for the Root Zone 
        please see details in the <a href="#table_of_references">Table of References</a> below. 
        References [0] to [9] refer to the Unicode Standard versions in which the
        corresponding code points were initially encoded. Reference [106] corresponds to a source
        given in [Proposal-Malayalam] justifying the inclusion of the corresponding code points. Entries in the table may have
        multiple source reference values.</p>
     ]]></description>
    <references>
      <reference id="0" comment="Any code point originally encoded in Unicode 1.1">The Unicode Standard 1.1</reference>
      <reference id="9" comment="Any code point originally encoded in Unicode 5.1">The Unicode Standard 5.1</reference>
      <reference id="106">Omniglot, “Malayalam (മലയാളം):” https://www.omniglot.com/writing/malayalam.htm (Accessed on 5th July, 2018)</reference>
      <reference id="3" comment="Any code point originally encoded in Unicode 3.0">The Unicode Standard 3.0</reference>
    </references>
  </meta>
  <data>
    <char cp="006F" tag="sc:Latn" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="006F" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0B20" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script near homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0D20" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script near homoglyph" />
      <var cp="101D" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script near homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0073" tag="sc:Latn" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0073" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0D1F" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script near homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0073 0073" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0073 0073" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0D1F 0D1F" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script near homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0B20" tag="sc:Orya" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="006F" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script near homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0B20" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0D20" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="101D" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0B9C" tag="sc:Taml" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0B9C" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0D1C" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0BAE" tag="sc:Taml" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0BAE" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0D25" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0BB5" tag="sc:Taml" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0BB5" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0D16" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0BBF" tag="sc:Taml" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0BBF" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0D3F" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0BC6" tag="sc:Taml" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0BC6" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0D46" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0BC7" tag="sc:Taml" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0BC7" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0D47" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D02" when="follows-C-V-or-M" tag="Anusvara sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM SIGN ANUSVARA" />
    <char cp="0D03" when="follows-C-V-or-M" tag="sc:Mlym Visarga" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM SIGN VISARGA" />
    <char cp="0D05" tag="sc:Mlym Vowel" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER A" />
    <char cp="0D06" tag="sc:Mlym Vowel" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER AA" />
    <char cp="0D07" tag="sc:Mlym Vowel" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER I" />
    <char cp="0D08" tag="sc:Mlym Vowel" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER II" />
    <char cp="0D09" tag="sc:Mlym Vowel" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER U" />
    <char cp="0D0A" tag="sc:Mlym Vowel" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER UU" />
    <char cp="0D0B" tag="sc:Mlym Vowel" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER VOCALIC R" />
    <char cp="0D0E" tag="sc:Mlym Vowel" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER E" />
    <char cp="0D0F" tag="sc:Mlym Vowel" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER EE" />
    <char cp="0D10" tag="sc:Mlym Vowel" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER AI" />
    <char cp="0D12" tag="sc:Mlym Vowel" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER O" />
    <char cp="0D13" tag="sc:Mlym Vowel" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER OO" />
    <char cp="0D14" tag="sc:Mlym Vowel" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER AU" />
    <char cp="0D15" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER KA" />
    <char cp="0D16" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER KHA">
      <var cp="0BB5" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D17" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER GA" />
    <char cp="0D18" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER GHA" />
    <char cp="0D19" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER NGA" />
    <char cp="0D1A" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER CA" />
    <char cp="0D1B" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER CHA" />
    <char cp="0D1C" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER JA">
      <var cp="0B9C" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D1D" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER JHA" />
    <char cp="0D1E" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER NYA" />
    <char cp="0D1F" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER TTA">
      <var cp="0073" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script near homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D1F 0D1F" comment="Added for cross-script variant">
      <var cp="0073 0073" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script near homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D20" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER TTHA">
      <var cp="006F" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script near homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0B20" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="101D" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D21" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER DDA" />
    <char cp="0D22" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER DDHA" />
    <char cp="0D23" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER NNA" />
    <char cp="0D24" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER TA" />
    <char cp="0D25" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER THA">
      <var cp="0BAE" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D26" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER DA" />
    <char cp="0D27" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER DHA" />
    <char cp="0D28" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER NA" />
    <char cp="0D28 0D4D" not-when="follows-B-X-or-H" ref="0 106">
      <var cp="0D7B" when="followed-by-0D31" type="blocked" />
      <var cp="0D7B 0D4D" when="followed-by-0D31" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D2A" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER PA" />
    <char cp="0D2B" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER PHA" />
    <char cp="0D2C" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER BA" />
    <char cp="0D2D" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER BHA" />
    <char cp="0D2E" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER MA" />
    <char cp="0D2F" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER YA" />
    <char cp="0D30" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER RA" />
    <char cp="0D31" not-when="follows-0D31" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER RRA">
      <var cp="1002" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D31 0D31" not-when="follows-0D31">
      <var cp="0D31 0D4D 0D31" not-when="follows-0D31-0D4D-or-followed-by-0D4D-0D31-or-R" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D31 0D31 0D4D 0D31" not-when="follows-0D31">
      <var cp="0D31 0D4D 0D31 0D31" not-when="followed-by-R" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D31 0D4D 0D31" not-when="follows-0D31">
      <var cp="0D31 0D31" not-when="follows-0D31-0D4D-or-followed-by-0D4D-0D31-or-R" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D31 0D4D 0D31 0D31" not-when="follows-0D31">
      <var cp="0D31 0D31 0D4D 0D31" not-when="followed-by-R" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D32" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER LA" />
    <char cp="0D33" not-when="follows-0D33" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER LLA" />
    <char cp="0D33 0D33" not-when="follows-0D33">
      <var cp="0D33 0D4D 0D33" not-when="follows-0D33-0D4D-or-followed-by-0D4D-0D33-or-R" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D33 0D33 0D4D 0D33" not-when="follows-0D33">
      <var cp="0D33 0D4D 0D33 0D33" not-when="followed-by-R" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D33 0D4D 0D33" not-when="follows-0D33">
      <var cp="0D33 0D33" not-when="follows-0D33-0D4D-or-followed-by-0D4D-0D33-or-R" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D33 0D4D 0D33 0D33" not-when="follows-0D33">
      <var cp="0D33 0D33 0D4D 0D33" not-when="followed-by-R" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D34" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER LLLA" />
    <char cp="0D35" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER VA" />
    <char cp="0D36" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER SHA" />
    <char cp="0D37" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER SSA" />
    <char cp="0D38" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER SA" />
    <char cp="0D39" tag="Consonant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER HA" />
    <char cp="0D3E" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM VOWEL SIGN AA" />
    <char cp="0D3F" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM VOWEL SIGN I">
      <var cp="0BBF" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D40" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM VOWEL SIGN II" />
    <char cp="0D41" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM VOWEL SIGN U" />
    <char cp="0D42" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM VOWEL SIGN UU" />
    <char cp="0D43" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM VOWEL SIGN VOCALIC R" />
    <char cp="0D46" when="follows-C" tag="Matra R sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM VOWEL SIGN E">
      <var cp="0BC6" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D47" when="follows-C" tag="Matra R sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM VOWEL SIGN EE">
      <var cp="0BC7" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D48" when="follows-C" tag="Matra R sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM VOWEL SIGN AI" />
    <char cp="0D4A" when="follows-C" tag="Matra R sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM VOWEL SIGN O" />
    <char cp="0D4B" when="follows-C" tag="Matra R sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM VOWEL SIGN OO" />
    <char cp="0D4D" when="follows-C-or-0D41" tag="Halant sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM SIGN VIRAMA" />
    <char cp="0D57" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Mlym" ref="0 106" comment="MALAYALAM AU LENGTH MARK" />
    <char cp="0D7A" not-when="follows-B-X-or-H" tag="Chillu sc:Mlym" ref="9 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER CHILLU NN" />
    <char cp="0D7B" not-when="follows-B-X-or-H" tag="Chillu sc:Mlym" ref="9 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER CHILLU N">
      <var cp="0D28 0D4D" when="followed-by-0D31" type="blocked" />
      <var cp="0D7B 0D4D" when="followed-by-0D31" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D7B 0D4D" when="follows-C-L-M-V-and-followed-by-03D1">
      <var cp="0D28 0D4D" when="followed-by-0D31" type="blocked" />
      <var cp="0D7B" when="followed-by-0D31" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D7C" not-when="follows-B-X-or-H" tag="Chillu sc:Mlym" ref="9 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER CHILLU RR" />
    <char cp="0D7D" not-when="follows-B-X-or-H" tag="Chillu sc:Mlym" ref="9 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER CHILLU L" />
    <char cp="0D7E" not-when="follows-B-X-or-H" tag="Chillu sc:Mlym" ref="9 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER CHILLU LL" />
    <char cp="0D7F" not-when="follows-B-X-or-H" tag="Chillu sc:Mlym" ref="9 106" comment="MALAYALAM LETTER CHILLU K" />
    <char cp="1002" tag="sc:Mymr" ref="3" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0D31" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="1002" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="101D" tag="sc:Mymr" ref="3" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="006F" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script near homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0B20" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0D20" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="101D" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
  </data>
  <!--Rules section goes here-->
  <rules>
    <!--Character class definitions go here-->
    <class name="C" from-tag="Consonant" comment="Any consonant" />
    <class name="V" from-tag="Vowel" comment="Any Malayalam independent vowel" />
    <class name="M" from-tag="Matra" comment="Any Malayalam vowel sign (matra)" />
    <class name="H" from-tag="Halant" comment="The Malayalam Halant/Virama" />
    <class name="B" from-tag="Anusvara" comment="The Malayalam Anusvara" />
    <class name="X" from-tag="Visarga" comment="The Malayalam Visarga" />
    <class name="L" from-tag="Chillu" comment="Any Malayalam chillu (consonant without any vowel sound)" />
    <class name="R" from-tag="R" comment="Any Malayalam reordrant vowel sign" />
    <!--Whole label evaluation and context rules go here-->
    <rule name="leading-combining-mark" comment="Default WLE rule matching labels with leading combining marks &#x235F;">
      <start />
      <union>
        <class property="gc:Mn" />
        <class property="gc:Mc" />
      </union>
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-C-or-0D41" comment="Section 7, WLE 1: Rule 1: H must be preceded by C or 0D41">
      <look-behind>
        <choice>
          <class by-ref="C" />
          <char cp="0D41" comment="MALAYALAM VOWEL SIGN U" />
        </choice>
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-C" comment="Section 7, WLE 2: M must be preceded by C">
      <look-behind>
        <class by-ref="C" />
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-C-V-or-M" comment="Section 7, WLE 3: B must be preceded by C, V or M and WLE 4: X must be preceded by C, V or M">
      <look-behind>
        <choice>
          <class by-ref="C" />
          <class by-ref="V" />
          <class by-ref="M" />
        </choice>
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-B-X-or-H" comment="Section 7, WLE 5: L cannot be preceded by B, X or H">
      <look-behind>
        <choice>
          <class by-ref="B" />
          <class by-ref="X" />
          <class by-ref="H" />
        </choice>
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="begins-with-L" comment="Section 7, WLE 6: Label does not begin with L">
      <start />
      <class by-ref="L" />
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-0D33" comment="Section 7, WLE 7. The character ള (0D33) cannot immediately follow ള (0D33), except as part of a defined sequence">
      <look-behind>
        <char cp="0D33" />
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-0D31" comment="Section 7, WLE 8. The character റ (0D31) cannot immediately follow റ (0D31), except as part of a defined sequence">
      <look-behind>
        <char cp="0D31" />
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-C-L-M-V-and-followed-by-03D1" comment="Section 7, WLE 9: Sequence 0D7B 0D4D must be preceded by C, L, M, V and must be followed by റ (0D31)">
      <look-behind>
        <choice>
          <class by-ref="C" />
          <class by-ref="L" />
          <class by-ref="M" />
          <class by-ref="V" />
        </choice>
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
      <look-ahead>
        <char cp="0D31" />
      </look-ahead>
    </rule>
    <rule name="reordrant-matra" comment="Reordrant matras, including sequence U+0D4D U+0D30">
      <choice>
        <class by-ref="R" />
        <char cp="0D4D 0D30" />
      </choice>
    </rule>
    <rule name="followed-by-R" comment="variant not defined if followed by reordrant matra">
      <anchor />
      <look-ahead>
        <rule by-ref="reordrant-matra" />
      </look-ahead>
    </rule>
    <rule name="followed-by-0D31" comment="Section 6.1, V1: A variant is defined when followed by 0D31">
      <anchor />
      <look-ahead>
        <char cp="0D31" />
      </look-ahead>
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-0D33-0D4D-or-followed-by-0D4D-0D33-or-R" comment="Section 6.1, V2: variant not defined if preceded by 0D33+Halant or followed by Halant+0D33 or R">
      <choice>
        <rule>
          <look-behind>
            <char cp="0D33 0D4D" />
          </look-behind>
          <anchor />
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <anchor />
          <look-ahead>
            <choice>
              <char cp="0D4D 0D33" />
              <rule by-ref="reordrant-matra" />
            </choice>
          </look-ahead>
        </rule>
      </choice>
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-0D31-0D4D-or-followed-by-0D4D-0D31-or-R" comment="Section 6.1, V3: variant not defined if preceded by 0D31+Halant or followed by Halant+0D31 or R">
      <choice>
        <rule>
          <look-behind>
            <char cp="0D31 0D4D" />
          </look-behind>
          <anchor />
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <anchor />
          <look-ahead>
            <choice>
              <char cp="0D4D 0D31" />
              <rule by-ref="reordrant-matra" />
            </choice>
          </look-ahead>
        </rule>
      </choice>
    </rule>
    <rule name="only-RRA" comment="Section 7, WLE 10: Labels consisting solely of the letter RRA are disallowed to limit cross-script interaction">
      <start />
      <char cp="0D31" count="1+" />
      <end />
    </rule>
    <!--Action elements go here - order defines precedence-->
    <action disp="invalid" match="leading-combining-mark" comment="labels with leading combining marks are invalid &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="invalid" match="begins-with-L" comment="Section 7, WLE 6: Label does not begin with L" />
    <action disp="invalid" match="only-RRA" comment="Section 7, WLE 10: Label cannot contain only RRA" />
    <action disp="invalid" any-variant="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="any variant label with a code point out of repertoire is invalid &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="blocked" any-variant="blocked" comment="any variant label containing blocked variants is blocked &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="allocatable" all-variants="allocatable" comment="variant labels with all variants allocatable are allocatable &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="valid" comment="catch all (default action) &#x235F;" />
  </rules>
</lgr>