<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<lgr xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:lgr-1.0">
  <meta>
    <version comment="Second Level Reference LGR">1</version>
    <date>2020-12-15</date>
    <language>und-Knda</language>
    <unicode-version>6.3.0</unicode-version>
    <description type="text/html"><![CDATA[
    <h1>Reference Label Generation Rules for the Kannada Script</h1>
    
    <h2>Overview</h2>
    <p>This document specifies a reference set of Label Generation Rules (LGR) for the Kannada script for the second level.
    The starting point for the development of this LGR can be found in the related Root Zone LGR [RZ-LGR-4-Knda]. 
    For details and additional background on the script, see "Proposal for a 
    Kannada Script Root Zone Label Generation Ruleset (LGR)" [Proposal-Kannada]. 
    The format of this file follows [RFC 7940].</p>

<h2>Repertoire</h2>
    <p>The repertoire contains 62 code points for letters covering Kannada, Tulu, Beary, Konkani, Havyaka, Kodava, among other languages written 
      using the Kannada script. The repertoire is a subset of [Unicode 6.3]. For more details, see Section 5, "Repertoire" in [Proposal-Kannada]. 
    (The proposal cited has been adopted for the Kannada script portion of the Root Zone LGR.)</p>

    <p>For the second level, the repertoire has been augmented with the HYPHEN-MINUS, and two sets of decimal digits:</p>
    <ul>
        <li>European (common) digits</li>
        <li>Kannada digits</li>
    </ul>
    <p>for a total of 83 repertoire elements.</p>
    
    <p>Code points outside the Kannada script that are listed in this file are targets
        for out-of-script variants and are identified by a reflexive (identity)
        variant of type "out-of-repertoire-var". They do not form part of the
        repertoire.</p>

      <p>Each code point or range is tagged with the script or scripts that
      the code point is used with, one or more tag values denoting character category, and one or more references documenting 
      sufficient justification for inclusion in the repertoire, see "References" below.
      Comments provide alternate names for some code points.</p>

  <h2>Variants</h2>
     <p>This reference LGR is designed for use in zones shared by more than one script.
     Where appropriate, cross-script variants have been defined to mutually exclude labels
     from different scripts that could otherwise be substituted by the users. Once a label
     has been delegated for one script, any variant labels from other scripts consisting of cross-script variants would be
     blocked. Any label containing at least one code point that is not a cross-script variant
     would be considered distinct. Because of that, even large numbers of defined cross-script
     variants generally do not lead to a high percentage of labels experiencing a collision.</p>

    <p>The Kannada and Telugu scripts are closely related to each other and there are many
    code points in both scripts which  can be confused with code points in the other script.
    This LGR defines many cross-script variants with Telugu as described in Section 6, "Variants", in "[Proposal-Kannada]".
    There are no in-script variants defined for Kannada.</p>

     <p><b>Digit Variants:</b> All Kannada digits are treated as semantic variants of the corresponding common (ASCII) digits. 
    By transitivity, they are also semantic variants of any native digits in scripts that also include the common digits.
    Such transitive relations are deemed to exist implicitly but are not listed explicitly in each reference LGR.
    (Omitting the listing of these other cross script digit variants does not affect index variant calculation, as the ASCII 
    digit variant being smallest would always be the index variant.)
    There is a homoglyph relation between most Telugu and Kannada digits, but as the Telugu LGR does not support native digits,
    this does not give rise to variants. In addition,
    Kannada digit ZERO is a cross-script homoglyph or near homoglyph of digit ZERO in many other scripts; 
    all of these are already implicit semantic variants by transitivity and therefore not listed here. 
    To keep digit variant sets manageable in zones where multiple scripts are present, no attempt has been made at identifying 
    cross-script variants among digits of <em>different numeric value</em> or between a digit in one script and a letter in another, 
    such as between digit zero and Latin letter 'o'. Other mechanisms may be required to prevent homograph labels.</p>

    <p><b>Variant Disposition:</b> All variants are of type "blocked" making labels that differ only 
    by these variants mutually exclusive:  whichever label containing either of these variants is chosen earlier 
    would be delegated, while any other equivalent variant label should be blocked. There is no preference among these variants.</p>
    <p>This LGR does not define allocatable variants.</p>
    <p>The specification of variants in this reference LGR follows the guidelines in [RFC 8228].</p>
      
    <h2>Character Classes</h2>
     <p>The structure of the Kannada script is similar to that of 
      other Indian scripts; it is particularly closely related to Telugu. The heart of the writing system is the <em>akshar</em>. 
     The basic characters are classified into three main categories:
      swara (vowels), vyanjana (consonants) and yogavahas (semiconsonants). </p>
    
    <p><b>Swaras (vowels):</b> There are thirteen vowels. When a vowel follows a consonant, it is 
    written with a diacritic rather than as a separate letter. Sometimes these are referred 
    to as vowel signs or matras. More details in Section 3.4.1, "Swaras (vowels)" in [Proposal-Kannada]. </p>

    <p><b>Yogavahas (semiconsonants):</b> The Yogavaha (part-vowel, part consonant) include two letters: </p>
    <ol>
    <li>The anusvara: ಅಂ /aṁ/.</li>
    <li>The visarga: ಅಃ /aḥ/. </li>
    </ol><p>See Section 3.4.2, "Yogavahas" in [Proposal-Kannada].</p>

    <p><b>Vyanjanas (consonants):</b> Two categories of consonant characters are 
    defined in Kannada: the structured consonants (vargeeya vyanjana) and the unstructured 
    consonants (avargeeya vyanjana). For the purpose of this LGR, all consonants are treated the same.
    More details in Section 3.4.3, "Vyanjanas (consonants)" of the 
    [Proposal-Kannada].</p>
    
    <p><b>Halant / Virama:</b> All consonant code points in Kannada 
    contain an implicit vowel ಅ /a/. The Unicode character U+0CCD, which 
    is the Kannada equivalent of the Devanagari Halant (or Virama), U+094D, is applied to 
    consonants to remove the implicit vowel. More 
    details in Section 3.4.4, "Implicit vowel ಅ (a) in consonants" in [Proposal-Kannada].</p>

    <p><b>Kannada Digits:</b> U+0CE6 to U+0CEF are a set of Kannada-specific digits. They are used in alternation with the European (common) digits.</p>

    <p><b>Common Digits:</b> U+0030 to U+0039 are the set of digits from the ASCII range. </p>
      
    <h2>Whole Label Evaluation (WLE) and Context Rules</h2>
    <h3>Common Rules</h3>
        <ul>
          <li><b>Hyphen Restrictions</b> &mdash; restrictions on the allowable placement of hyphens (no leading/ending hyphen
             and no hyphen in positions 3 and 4). These restrictions are described in section 4.2.3.1 of RFC 5891 [150]. 
             They are implemented here as context rule on U+002D (-) HYPHEN-MINUS.</li>
          <li><b>Leading Combining Marks</b>   &mdash;  restrictions on the allowable placement of combining marks
             (no leading combining mark). This rule is described in section 4.2.3.2 of RFC 5891 [150].</li>
          <li><b>Digit-mixing</b> &mdash; no mixing between different digit sets (European and Kannada digits)
             is allowed; implemented here as a WLE rule with associated action.</li>
    </ul>
    <h3>Default Actions</h3>
    <p>Actions include the default actions for LGRs as well as that needed to
        invalidate labels with misplaced combining marks. They are marked with &#x235F;.
        For a description see [RFC 7940].</p> 
        
    <h3>Kannada-specific Rules</h3>
    <p>These rules have been formulated so that they can be adopted for  LGR specification.</p>
    <p>The following symbols are used in the WLE rules: 
    <br/>C    →    Consonant
    <br/>M    →    Matra
    <br/>V    →    Vowel
    <br/>B    →    Anusvara
    <br/>X    →    Visarga
    <br/>H    →    Halant / Virama
    </p>
    
    <p>The rules are: </p>
     <ul>
     <li>1. H: must be preceded by C</li>
     <li>2. M: must be preceded by C</li>
     <li>3. B: must be preceded by C, V or M</li>
     <li>4. X: must be preceded by C, V or M</li>
     <li>5. V: cannot be preceded by H</li>
     </ul>
    
     <p>More details in Section 7, "Whole Label Evaluation Rules (WLE)" of [Proposal-Kannada].</p>
    
    <h2>Methodology and Contributors</h2>
    <p>This reference LGR for Kannada for the 2nd Level has been developed by Michel Suignard and Asmus Freytag, based on the Root Zone LGR for Kannada 
    and information contained or referenced therein, see [RZ-LGR-4-Knda]. Suitable extensions for the second level have been applied according to the [Guidelines]. 
    The original proposal for a Root Zone LGR for the Kannada script, that this reference LGR is based on, was developed by the Neo-Brahmi Generation Panel (NBGP).
    For more information on methodology and contributors to the underlying Root Zone LGR, see [Proposal-Kannada].</p>

    <h2>References</h2> 
    <p>The following general references are cited in this document:</p>
    <dl class="references">
    <dt>[Guidelines]</dt>
    <dd>ICANN, "Guidelines for Developing Reference LGRs for the Second Level, (Los Angeles, California: ICANN, 27 May 2020), https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/lgr-guidelines-second-level-06jan16-en.pdf</dd>

    <dt>[Proposal-Kannada]</dt> 
    <dd>Neo-Brahmi Generation Panel, “Proposal for a Kannada Script Root Zone Label Generation Ruleset (LGR)”, 6 March 2019, https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/proposal-kannada-lgr-06mar19-en.pdf</dd>

    <dt>[RFC 7940]</dt>
     <dd>Davies, K. and A. Freytag, "Representing Label Generation Rulesets Using XML", RFC 7940, August 2016, http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7940</dd> 
     
    <dt>[RFC 8228]</dt>
    <dd>A. Freytag, "Guidance on Designing Label Generation Rulesets (LGRs) Supporting Variant Labels", RFC 8228, August 2017,
    https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8228</dd>
      <dt>[RZ-LGR-Overview]</dt>
       <dd>Integration Panel, "Root Zone Label Generation Rules - LGR-4: Overview and Summary", 5 November 2020 (PDF), https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/lgr-4-overview-05nov20-en.pdf</dd>

     <dt>[RZ-LGR-4-Knda]</dt>
     <dd>ICANN, Root Zone Label Generation Rules for the Kannada Script (und-Knda) , 5 November 2020 (XML)
https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/lgr-4-kannada-script-05nov20-en.xml</dd>
     <dt>[Unicode 6.3]</dt>
     <dd>The Unicode Consortium. The Unicode Standard, Version 6.3.0, (Mountain View, CA: The Unicode Consortium, 2013. ISBN 978-1-936213-08-5) 
     http://www.unicode.org/versions/Unicode6.3.0/</dd>
     </dl>
      <p>For references consulted particularly in designing the repertoire for the Kannada script for the second level 
      please see details in the <a href="#table_of_references">Table of References</a> below. 
      Reference [0] refers to the Unicode Standard version in which the
      corresponding code points were initially encoded. References [110] and above correspond to sources
      given in [Proposal-Kannada] justifying the inclusion of the corresponding code points. Entries in the table may have
      multiple source reference values. Reference [150] indicates the source for common rules.</p>

]]></description>
    <references>
      <reference id="0" comment="Any code point originally encoded in Unicode 1.1">The Unicode Standard 1.1</reference>
      <reference id="110">ಕನ್ನಡ ಮಧ್ಯಮ ವ್ಯಾಕರಣ, ತೀ.ನಂ. ಶ್ರೀಕಂಠಯ್ಯ, ಗೀತಾ ಬುಕ್ ಹೌಸ್, ಮೈಸೂರು, ೨೦೦೧ /Kannada Madhyama Vyakarana/ (An Intermediate Kannada Grammar), T. N. Sreekantaiya, Geetha Book House, Mysore, 2001. </reference>
      <reference id="111">Omniglot, Kannada (ಕನ್ನಡ), https://www.omniglot.com/writing/kannada.htm</reference>
      <reference id="150">RFC 5891, Internationalized Domain Names in Applications (IDNA): Protocol http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5891</reference>
    </references>
  </meta>
  <data>
    <char cp="002D" not-when="hyphen-minus-disallowed" tag="Hyphen sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="HYPHEN-MINUS; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0030" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT ZERO; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0CE6" type="blocked" comment="Kannada digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0031" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT ONE; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0CE7" type="blocked" comment="Kannada digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0032" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT TWO; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0CE8" type="blocked" comment="Kannada digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0033" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT THREE; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0CE9" type="blocked" comment="Kannada digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0034" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT FOUR; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0CEA" type="blocked" comment="Kannada digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0035" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT FIVE; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0CEB" type="blocked" comment="Kannada digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0036" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT SIX; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0CEC" type="blocked" comment="Kannada digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0037" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT SEVEN; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0CED" type="blocked" comment="Kannada digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0038" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT EIGHT; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0CEE" type="blocked" comment="Kannada digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0039" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT NINE; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0CEF" type="blocked" comment="Kannada digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C02" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C02" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0C82" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C03" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C03" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0C83" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C05" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C05" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0C85" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C06" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C06" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0C86" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C07" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C07" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0C87" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C08" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C08" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0C88" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C10" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C10" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0C90" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C12" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C12" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0C92" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C13" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C13" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0C93" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C14" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C14" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0C94" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C16" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C16" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0C96" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C17" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C17" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0C97" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C1C" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C1C" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0C9C" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C1D" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C1D" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0C9D" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C1E" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C1E" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0C9E" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C1F" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C1F" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0C9F" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C20" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C20" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CA0" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C21" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C21" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CA1" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C22" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C22" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CA2" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C23" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C23" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CA3" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C25" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C25" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CA5" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C26" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C26" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CA6" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C27" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C27" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CA7" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C28" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C28" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CA8" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C2C" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C2C" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CAC" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C2D" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C2D" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CAD" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C2E" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C2E" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CAE" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C2F" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C2F" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CAF" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C30" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C30" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CB0" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C32" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C32" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CB2" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C33" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C33" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CB3" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C3F" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C3F" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CBF" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C41" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C41" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CC1" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C43" tag="sc:Telu" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C43" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
      <var cp="0CC3" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C82" when="follows-C-V-or-M" tag="Anusvara sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C02" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C83" when="follows-C-V-or-M" tag="sc:Knda Visarga" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C03" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C85" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Knda Vowel" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C05" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C86" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Knda Vowel" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C06" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C87" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Knda Vowel" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C07" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C88" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Knda Vowel" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C08" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C89" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Knda Vowel" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0C8A" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Knda Vowel" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0C8B" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Knda Vowel" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0C8E" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Knda Vowel" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0C8F" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Knda Vowel" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0C90" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Knda Vowel" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C10" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C92" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Knda Vowel" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C12" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C93" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Knda Vowel" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C13" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C94" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Knda Vowel" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C14" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C95" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0C96" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C16" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C97" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C17" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C98" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0C99" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0C9A" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0C9B" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0C9C" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C1C" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C9D" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C1D" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C9E" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C1E" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C9F" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C1F" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CA0" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C20" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CA1" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C21" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CA2" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C22" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CA3" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C23" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CA4" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CA5" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C25" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CA6" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C26" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CA7" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C27" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CA8" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C28" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CAA" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CAB" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CAC" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C2C" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CAD" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C2D" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CAE" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C2E" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CAF" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C2F" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CB0" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C30" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CB2" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C32" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CB3" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C33" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CB5" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CB6" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CB7" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CB8" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CB9" tag="Consonant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CBE" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CBF" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C3F" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CC0" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CC1" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C41" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CC2" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CC3" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111">
      <var cp="0C43" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CC6" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CC7" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CC8" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CCA" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CCB" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CCC" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" />
    <char cp="0CCD" when="follows-C" tag="Halant sc:Knda" ref="0 110 111" comment="= Halant" />
    <char cp="0CE6" tag="Kannada-digit sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="KANNADA DIGIT ZERO">
      <var cp="0030" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CE7" tag="Kannada-digit sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="KANNADA DIGIT ONE">
      <var cp="0031" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CE8" tag="Kannada-digit sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="KANNADA DIGIT TWO">
      <var cp="0032" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CE9" tag="Kannada-digit sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="KANNADA DIGIT THREE">
      <var cp="0033" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CEA" tag="Kannada-digit sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="KANNADA DIGIT FOUR">
      <var cp="0034" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CEB" tag="Kannada-digit sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="KANNADA DIGIT FIVE">
      <var cp="0035" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CEC" tag="Kannada-digit sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="KANNADA DIGIT SIX">
      <var cp="0036" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CED" tag="Kannada-digit sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="KANNADA DIGIT SEVEN">
      <var cp="0037" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CEE" tag="Kannada-digit sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="KANNADA DIGIT EIGHT">
      <var cp="0038" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CEF" tag="Kannada-digit sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="KANNADA DIGIT NINE">
      <var cp="0039" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
  </data>
  <!--Rules section goes here-->
  <rules>
    <!--Character class definitions go here-->
    <class name="C" from-tag="Consonant" ref="110 111" comment="Any Kannada consonant" />
    <class name="V" from-tag="Vowel" ref="110 111" comment="Any Kannada independent vowel" />
    <class name="M" from-tag="Matra" ref="110 111" comment="Any Kannada vowel sign (matra)" />
    <class name="H" from-tag="Halant" ref="110 111" comment="The Kannada Halant / Virama" />
    <class name="common-digits" from-tag="Common-digit" comment="Digits from the ASCII range; &#x235F;" />
    <class name="kannada-digits" from-tag="Kannada-digit" comment="Kannada digits" />
    <class name="hyphen" from-tag="Hyphen" comment="The Hyphen-minus character &#x235F;" />
    <!--Whole label evaluation and context rules go here-->
    <rule name="leading-combining-mark" ref="150" comment="RFC 5891 restrictions on placement of combining marks &#x235F;">
      <start />
      <union>
        <class property="gc:Mn" />
        <class property="gc:Mc" />
      </union>
    </rule>
    <rule name="hyphen-minus-disallowed" ref="150" comment="RFC 5891 restrictions on placement of U+002D &#x235F;">
      <choice>
        <rule comment="no leading hyphen">
          <look-behind>
            <start />
          </look-behind>
          <anchor />
        </rule>
        <rule comment="no trailing hyphen">
          <anchor />
          <look-ahead>
            <end />
          </look-ahead>
        </rule>
        <rule comment="no consecutive hyphens in third and fourth position in the label">
          <look-behind>
            <start />
            <any />
            <any />
            <class by-ref="hyphen" />
          </look-behind>
          <anchor />
        </rule>
      </choice>
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-C" comment="Section 7, WLE 1: H must be preceded by C; WLE 2: M must be preceded by C">
      <look-behind>
        <class by-ref="C" />
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-C-V-or-M" comment="Section 7, WLE 3: Anusvara must be preceded by C, V or M; WLE 4: Visarga must be preceded by C, V or M">
      <look-behind>
        <choice>
          <class by-ref="C" />
          <class by-ref="V" />
          <class by-ref="M" />
        </choice>
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-H" comment="Section 7, WLE 5: V cannot be preceded by H">
      <look-behind>
        <class by-ref="H" />
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="digit-mixing" comment="restrictions on mixing digits">
      <choice>
        <rule>
          <class by-ref="common-digits" />
          <any count="0+" />
          <class by-ref="kannada-digits" />
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <class by-ref="kannada-digits" />
          <any count="0+" />
          <class by-ref="common-digits" />
        </rule>
      </choice>
    </rule>
    <!--Action elements go here - order defines precedence-->
    <action disp="invalid" match="leading-combining-mark" ref="150" comment="labels with leading combining marks are invalid &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="invalid" match="digit-mixing" comment="a label violating the restriction on digit mixing is invalid" />
    <action disp="invalid" any-variant="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="any variant label with a code point out of repertoire is invalid &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="blocked" any-variant="blocked" comment="any variant label containing blocked variants is blocked &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="allocatable" all-variants="allocatable" comment="variant labels with all variants allocatable are allocatable &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="valid" comment="catch all (default action) &#x235F;" />
  </rules>
</lgr>