<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<lgr xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:lgr-1.0">
  <meta>
    <version comment="Second Level Reference LGR">1</version>
    <date>2020-12-15</date>
    <language>und-Gujr</language>
    <unicode-version>6.3.0</unicode-version>
    <description type="text/html"><![CDATA[
    <h1>Reference Label Generation Rules for the Gujarati Script</h1>
    
    <h2>Overview</h2>
    <p>This document specifies a reference set of Label Generation Rules (LGR) for the Gujarati script for the second level.
    The starting point for the development of this LGR can be found in the related Root Zone LGR [RZ-LGR-4-Gujr]. 
    For details and additional background on the script, see "Proposal for a
    Gujarati Script Label Generation Ruleset for the Root Zone" [Proposal-Gujarati]. 
    The format of this file follows [RFC 7940].</p>

    <h2>Repertoire</h2>
    <p>This LGR contains 65 code points for letters covering multiple languages written using the Gujarati script and ranging from 1 to 4 on the [EGIDS] scale.
    The repertoire   is a subset of [Unicode 6.3]. For more detail, see Section 5, "Repertoire" in [Proposal-Gujarati]. 
    (The proposal cited has been adopted for the Gujarati script portion of the Root Zone LGR.)</p>

    <p>For the second level, the repertoire has been augmented with the Gujarati digits, U+0AR6 to U+0AEF, ASCII digits U+0030 to U+0039, and U+002D HYPHEN-MINUS
    for a total of 86 repertoire elements.</p>

      <p>Each code point or range is tagged with the script or scripts that
      the code point is used with, one or more tag values denoting character category, and one or more references documenting 
      sufficient justification for inclusion in the repertoire, see "References" below.</p>

    <h2>Variants</h2>
    <p>This LGR defines no variants for letters. For details, see Section 6, "Variants" in [Proposal-Gujarati].</p>

    <p><b>Digit Variants:</b> All Gujarati digits are treated as semantic variants of the corresponding common (ASCII) digits. 
    By transitivity, they are also semantic variants of any native digits in scripts that also include the common digits.
    Such variant relations are deemed to exist implicitly by transitivity but are not listed explicitly in each reference LGR.
    (Omitting the listing of these other cross script digit variants does not affect index variant calculation, as the ASCII 
    digit variant being smallest would always be the index variant.)
    Note that in addition to a transitive semantic variant relation, Gujarati digits ZERO, TWO, FOUR, and EIGHT are cross-script 
    homoglyphs or near homoglyphs with      Devanagari digits of the same value. Digit FOUR is also a variant of Oriya digit FOUR.
    Gujarati digit ZERO is a cross-script homoglyph or near homoglyph of digit ZERO in many other scripts; 
    these are already implicit semantic variants by transitivity and therefore not listed here. </p>

    <p>Some Gujarati letters share forms with digits: U+0AB0 GUJARATI LETTER RA is a homoglyph variant of U+0aE8 GUJARATI DIGIT TWO. 
    U+0AAA GUJARATI LETTER PA is a homoglyph variant of U+0AEB GUJARATI DIGIT FIVE. By transitivity, the ASCII digits TWO and FIVE
    are also variants of the respective letters, and so are all other corresponding native digits TWO and FIVE, even though not
    explicitly listed here.</p>

    <p>To keep digit variant sets manageable in zones where multiple scripts are present, no attempt has been made at identifying 
    cross-script variants among digits of different numeric value, such as between Gujarati digit ONE and Bengali digit SEVEN;
    or between a digit in one script and a letter in another, such as between digit zero and Latin letter 'o'.</p>

    <h2>Character Classes</h2>
    <p>Gujarati is an alphasyllabary and the heart of the writing system is 
    the <em>akshar</em>. This is the unit which is instinctively recognized by users of the script.
    As encoded, the writing system of Gujarati is composed of Consonants, 
    the Implicit Vowel Killer: Halant, Vowels, Anusvara, Candrabindu, Nukta, Visarga
    and Avagraha.</p>
    
    <p><b>Consonants:</b> Gujarati consonants contain an implicit vowel schwa /ə/. The 
     traditional classification categorizes them according to their phonetic 
    properties. There are 5 Varga groups (classes) and one non-Varga group. Each varga, 
    which corresponds to a particular stop, contains five consonants classified as per their properties. 
    The first four consonants are classified on the basis of Voicing and Aspiration and the 
    last is the corresponding nasal. More details in Section 3.4.1, "The Consonants" of the 
    [Proposal-Gujarati].</p>
    
    <p><b>Halant:</b> All consonants contain the implicit vowel (schwa). A special
    sign is needed to denote that this implicit vowel is stripped off. This is known as the 
    Halant (્). The Halant thus joins two consonants and creates conjuncts, which 
    generally combine 2 to 4 consonants. In rare cases the Halant can join up to 5 consonants. 
    More details in Section 3.4.2, "The Implicit Vowel Killer: Halant" in [Proposal-Gujarati].</p>

    <p><b>Vowels and Matras:</b> Separate symbols exist for all Vowels, which are either pronounced independently 
    at the beginning or attached to a consonant. To indicate the latter (other than the implicit one), 
    a Vowel modifier (matra) is attached to the consonant. Since the consonant has a built-in schwa, 
    there are equivalent Matras for all vowels excepting the અ (U+0A85).  More details in Section 
    3.4.3, "Vowels" in [Proposal-Gujarati].</p>

    <p><b>Anusvara:</b> In Gujarati, the Anusvara has a dual function. On the one hand, it acts as 
    homorganic nasal, that is, it replaces a conjunct group of a Nasal Consonant+Halant+Consonant 
    belonging to that particular varga. On the other hand, before a non-varga consonant the 
    anusvara represents a nasal sound. Gujarati and its dialects prefer the anusvara to the 
    corresponding half-nasal. More details in Section 3.4.4, "The Anusvara" in [Proposal-Gujarati].</p>

    <p><b>Nukta:</b> Traditionally Gujarati does not admit the Nukta. Gujarati grammarians 
    in their inventory of the Gujarati alphabet do not admit this diacritic. However, 
    the Nukta is used to represent content where Perso-Arabic characters have to be 
    transliterated. It follows specific consonants listed in set C1.
     More details in Section 3.4.6, "Nukta" in [Proposal-Gujarati].</p>

    <p><b>Visarga and Avagraha:</b> The Visarga is frequently used in Sanskrit and represents 
    a sound very close to /h/, as in દુઃખ /du:kh/ sorrow, unhappiness. It is used sparingly 
    in Gujarati with a few words borrowed from Sanskrit. The Avagraha is rarely used and 
    excluded from the LGR. More details in Section 3.4.7, 
    "Visarga and Avagraha" in [Proposal-Gujarati].</p>
    
    <p><b>Common Digits:</b> U+0030 to U+0039 are the set of digits from the ASCII range. </p>

    <p><b>Gujarati Digits:</b> U+0AE6 to U+0AEF are a set of Gujarati-specific digits.</p>

    <h2>Whole Label Evaluation (WLE) and Context Rules</h2>
    <h3>Common Rules</h3>
        <ul>
          <li><b>Hyphen Restrictions</b> &mdash; restrictions on the allowable placement of hyphens (no leading/ending hyphen
             and no hyphen in positions 3 and 4). These restrictions are described in section 4.2.3.1 of RFC 5891 [150]. 
             They are implemented here as context rule on U+002D (-) HYPHEN-MINUS.</li>
          <li><b>Leading Combining Marks</b>   &mdash;  restrictions on the allowable placement of combining marks
             (no leading combining mark). This rule is described in section 4.2.3.2 of RFC 5891 [150].</li>
          <li><b>Digit-mixing</b> &mdash; no mixing between different digit sets (European and Gujarati digits)
             is allowed; implemented here as a WLE rule with associated action.</li>
    </ul>

    <h3>Default Actions</h3>
    <p>Actions include the default actions for LGRs as well as that needed to
     invalidate labels with misplaced combining marks. They are marked with &#x235F;.
     For a description see [RFC 7940].</p> 
        
    <h3>Gujarati-specific Rules</h3>
    <p>These rules have been drafted to ensure that the prospective Gujarati label conforms
    to akshar formation norms as desired in Gujarati script.  These norms are exclusively 
    presented as context rules.    </p>
    <p>The following symbols are used in the WLE rules: 
    <br/>C    →    Consonant
    <br/>M    →    Matra
    <br/>V    →    Vowel
    <br/>B    →    Anusvara
    <br/>X    →    Visarga
    <br/>H    →    Halant/Virama
    <br/>N    →    Nukta
    <br/>C1   →    Consonants used with Nukta
    </p>
    
    <p>The rules are: </p>
     <ul>
     <li>1. N: must be preceded by any of the specific set of Consonants (C1)</li>
     <li>2. H: must be preceded either by C or N</li>
     <li>3. X: must be preceded by any of V, C, N or M</li>
     <li>4. B: must be preceded by any of V, C, N or M</li>
     <li>5. M: must be preceded either by C or N</li>
     </ul>

     <p>More details in Section 7,"Whole Label Evaluation Rules (WLE)" in [Proposal-Gujarati].</p>
    
    <h2>Methodology and Contributors</h2>
    <p>This reference LGR for the Gujarati script for the 2nd Level has been developed by Michel Suignard and Asmus Freytag, based on the Root Zone LGR for Gujarati 
      and information contained or referenced therein, see [RZ-LGR-4-Gujr]. Suitable extensions for the second level have been applied according to the [Guidelines]. 
      The original proposal for a Root Zone LGR for the Gujarati script, that this reference LGR is based on, was developed by the Neo-Brahmi Generation Panel (NBGP). 
      For more information on methodology and contributors to the underlying Root Zone LGR, see Sections 4 and 8 in [Proposal-Gujarati], as well as [RZ-LGR-Overview].</p>

    <h2>References</h2> 
    <p>The following general references are cited in this document:</p>
    <dl class="references">
    <dt>[Guidelines]</dt>
    <dd>ICANN, "Guidelines for Developing Reference LGRs for the Second Level, (Los Angeles, California: ICANN, 27 May 2020), https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/lgr-guidelines-second-level-06jan16-en.pdf</dd>

    <dt>[EGIDS]</dt>
     <dd>Expanded Graded Intergenerational Disruption Scale, https://www.ethnologue.com/about/language-status 
     </dd>

    <dt>[Proposal-Gujarati]</dt>
     <dd>Neo-Brahmi Generation Panel, "Proposal for a Gujarati Script Root Zone Label Generation Ruleset (LGR)", 6 March 2019, https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/proposal-gujarati-lgr-06mar19-en.pdf</dd>

    <dt>[RFC 7940]</dt>
     <dd>Davies, K. and A. Freytag, "Representing Label Generation Rulesets Using XML", RFC 7940, August 2016, http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7940</dd> 
    <dt>[RZ-LGR-Overview]</dt>
     <dd>Integration Panel, "Root Zone Label Generation Rules - LGR-4: Overview and Summary", 5 November 2020 (PDF), https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/lgr-4-overview-05nov20-en.pdf</dd>

    <dt>[RZ-LGR-4-Gujr]</dt>
     <dd>ICANN, Root Zone Label Generation Rules for the Gujarati Script (und-Gujr) , 5 November 2020 (XML)
        https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/lgr-4-gujarati-script-05nov20-en.xml</dd>
    <dt>[Unicode 6.3]</dt>
     <dd>The Unicode Consortium. The Unicode Standard, Version 6.3.0, (Mountain View, CA: The Unicode Consortium, 2013. ISBN 978-1-936213-08-5) 
     http://www.unicode.org/versions/Unicode6.3.0/</dd>
    </dl>
    <p>For references consulted particularly in designing the repertoire for the Gujarati script for the second level 
     please see details in the <a href="#table_of_references">Table of References</a> below. 
     Reference [0] refers to the Unicode Standard version in which the
     corresponding code points were initially encoded. Reference [101] corresponds to a source
     justifying the inclusion of the corresponding code points. Entries in the table may have
     multiple source reference values. Reference [150] indicates the source for common rules.</p>

]]></description>
    <references>
      <reference id="0" comment="Any code point originally encoded in Unicode 1.1">The Unicode Standard 1.1</reference>
      <reference id="6" comment="Any code point originally encoded in Unicode 4.0">The Unicode Standard 4.0</reference>
      <reference id="101">Omniglot, &quot;Gujarati&quot;, https://www.omniglot.com/writing/gujarati.htm (Accessed on 6 Jan. 2018)</reference>
      <reference id="150">RFC 5891, Internationalized Domain Names in Applications (IDNA): Protocol http://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5891</reference>
    </references>
  </meta>
  <data>
    <char cp="002D" not-when="hyphen-minus-disallowed" tag="Hyphen sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="HYPHEN-MINUS; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0030" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT ZERO; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0AE6" type="blocked" comment="Gujarati digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0031" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT ONE; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0AE7" type="blocked" comment="Gujarati digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0032" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT TWO; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0AB0" type="blocked" comment="Gujarati variant" />
      <var cp="0AE8" type="blocked" comment="Gujarati digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0033" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT THREE; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0AE9" type="blocked" comment="Gujarati digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0034" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT FOUR; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0AEA" type="blocked" comment="Gujarati digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0035" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT FIVE; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0AAA" type="blocked" comment="Gujarati variant" />
      <var cp="0AEB" type="blocked" comment="Gujarati digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0036" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT SIX; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0AEC" type="blocked" comment="Gujarati digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0037" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT SEVEN; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0AED" type="blocked" comment="Gujarati digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0038" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT EIGHT; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0AEE" type="blocked" comment="Gujarati digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0039" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT NINE; &#x235F;">
      <var cp="0AEF" type="blocked" comment="Gujarati digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0A82" when="follows-V-C-N-or-M" tag="Anusvara sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A83" when="follows-V-C-N-or-M" tag="sc:Gujr Visarga" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A85" tag="sc:Gujr Vowel" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A86" tag="sc:Gujr Vowel" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A87" tag="sc:Gujr Vowel" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A88" tag="sc:Gujr Vowel" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A89" tag="sc:Gujr Vowel" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A8A" tag="sc:Gujr Vowel" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A8B" tag="sc:Gujr Vowel" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A8C" tag="sc:Gujr Vowel" ref="6 101" />
    <char cp="0A8D" tag="sc:Gujr Vowel" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A8F" tag="sc:Gujr Vowel" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A90" tag="sc:Gujr Vowel" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A91" tag="sc:Gujr Vowel" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A93" tag="sc:Gujr Vowel" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A94" tag="sc:Gujr Vowel" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A95" tag="C1 Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A96" tag="C1 Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A97" tag="C1 Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A98" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A99" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A9A" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A9B" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A9C" tag="C1 Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A9D" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A9E" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0A9F" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AA0" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AA1" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AA2" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AA3" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AA4" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AA5" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AA6" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AA7" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AA8" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AAA" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101">
      <var cp="0035" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
      <var cp="0AEB" type="blocked" comment="Gujarati digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0AAB" tag="C1 Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AAC" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AAD" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AAE" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AAF" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AB0" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101">
      <var cp="0032" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
      <var cp="0AE8" type="blocked" comment="Gujarati digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0AB2" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AB3" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AB5" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AB6" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AB7" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AB8" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AB9" tag="Consonant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0ABC" when="follows-specific-C" tag="Nukta sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0ABE" when="follows-C-or-N" tag="Matra sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0ABF" when="follows-C-or-N" tag="Matra sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AC0" when="follows-C-or-N" tag="Matra sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AC1" when="follows-C-or-N" tag="Matra sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AC2" when="follows-C-or-N" tag="Matra sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AC3" when="follows-C-or-N" tag="Matra sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AC4" when="follows-C-or-N" tag="Matra sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AC5" when="follows-C-or-N" tag="Matra sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AC7" when="follows-C-or-N" tag="Matra sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AC8" when="follows-C-or-N" tag="Matra sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AC9" when="follows-C-or-N" tag="Matra sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0ACB" when="follows-C-or-N" tag="Matra sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0ACC" when="follows-C-or-N" tag="Matra sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0ACD" when="follows-C-or-N" tag="Halant sc:Gujr" ref="0 101" />
    <char cp="0AE6" tag="Gujarati-digit sc:Gujr" ref="0" comment="GUJARATI DIGIT ZERO">
      <var cp="0030" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0AE7" tag="Gujarati-digit sc:Gujr" ref="0" comment="GUJARATI DIGIT ONE">
      <var cp="0031" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0AE8" tag="Gujarati-digit sc:Gujr" ref="0" comment="GUJARATI DIGIT TWO">
      <var cp="0032" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
      <var cp="0AB0" type="blocked" comment="Gujarati variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0AE9" tag="Gujarati-digit sc:Gujr" ref="0" comment="GUJARATI DIGIT THREE">
      <var cp="0033" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0AEA" tag="Gujarati-digit sc:Gujr" ref="0" comment="GUJARATI DIGIT FOUR">
      <var cp="0034" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0AEB" tag="Gujarati-digit sc:Gujr" ref="0" comment="GUJARATI DIGIT FIVE">
      <var cp="0035" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
      <var cp="0AAA" type="blocked" comment="Gujarati variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0AEC" tag="Gujarati-digit sc:Gujr" ref="0" comment="GUJARATI DIGIT SIX">
      <var cp="0036" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0AED" tag="Gujarati-digit sc:Gujr" ref="0" comment="GUJARATI DIGIT SEVEN">
      <var cp="0037" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0AEE" tag="Gujarati-digit sc:Gujr" ref="0" comment="GUJARATI DIGIT EIGHT">
      <var cp="0038" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0AEF" tag="Gujarati-digit sc:Gujr" ref="0" comment="GUJARATI DIGIT NINE">
      <var cp="0039" type="blocked" comment="ASCII digit variant" />
    </char>
  </data>
  <!--Rules section goes here-->
  <rules>
    <!--Character class definitions go here-->
    <class name="C" from-tag="Consonant" comment="Any Gujarati consonant" />
    <class name="V" from-tag="Vowel" comment="Any Gujarati vowel letter" />
    <class name="M" from-tag="Matra" comment="Any Gujarati vowel sign" />
    <class name="N" from-tag="Nukta" comment="The Gujarati Nukta" />
    <class name="C1" from-tag="C1" comment="Consonants used with Gujarati Nukta" />
    <class name="common-digits" from-tag="Common-digit" comment="Digits from the ASCII range; &#x235F;" />
    <class name="gujarati-digits" from-tag="Gujarati-digit" comment="Gujarati digits" />
    <class name="hyphen" from-tag="Hyphen" comment="The Hyphen-minus character &#x235F;" />
    <!--Whole label evaluation and context rules go here-->
    <rule name="leading-combining-mark" ref="150" comment="RFC 5891 restrictions on placement of combining marks &#x235F;">
      <start />
      <union>
        <class property="gc:Mn" />
        <class property="gc:Mc" />
      </union>
    </rule>
    <rule name="hyphen-minus-disallowed" ref="150" comment="RFC 5891 restrictions on placement of U+002D &#x235F;">
      <choice>
        <rule comment="no leading hyphen">
          <look-behind>
            <start />
          </look-behind>
          <anchor />
        </rule>
        <rule comment="no trailing hyphen">
          <anchor />
          <look-ahead>
            <end />
          </look-ahead>
        </rule>
        <rule comment="no consecutive hyphens in third and fourth position in the label">
          <look-behind>
            <start />
            <any />
            <any />
            <class by-ref="hyphen" />
          </look-behind>
          <anchor />
        </rule>
      </choice>
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-specific-C" comment="Section 7, WLE 1: N must be preceded by a specific set of Cs">
      <look-behind>
        <class by-ref="C1" />
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-C-or-N" comment="Section 7, WLE 2: Halant must be preceded by C or N; WLE 5: M: must be preceded by C or N">
      <look-behind>
        <choice>
          <class by-ref="C" />
          <class by-ref="N" />
        </choice>
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-V-C-N-or-M" comment="Section 7, WLE 3 and WLE 4: Visarga and Anusvara must be preceded by V, C, N or M">
      <look-behind>
        <choice>
          <class by-ref="V" />
          <class by-ref="C" />
          <class by-ref="N" />
          <class by-ref="M" />
        </choice>
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="digit-mixing" comment="restrictions on mixing digits">
      <choice>
        <rule>
          <class by-ref="common-digits" />
          <any count="0+" />
          <class by-ref="gujarati-digits" />
        </rule>
        <rule>
          <class by-ref="gujarati-digits" />
          <any count="0+" />
          <class by-ref="common-digits" />
        </rule>
      </choice>
    </rule>
    <!--Action elements go here - order defines precedence-->
    <action disp="invalid" match="leading-combining-mark" ref="150" comment="labels with leading combining marks are invalid &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="invalid" match="digit-mixing" comment="a label violating the restriction on digit mixing is invalid" />
    <action disp="invalid" any-variant="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="any variant label with a code point out of repertoire is invalid &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="blocked" any-variant="blocked" comment="any variant label containing blocked variants is blocked &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="allocatable" all-variants="allocatable" comment="variant labels with all variants allocatable are allocatable &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="valid" comment="catch all (default action) &#x235F;" />
  </rules>
</lgr>