<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<lgr xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:lgr-1.0">
  <meta>
    <version comment="Second Level Reference LGR">2</version>
    <date>2022-05-31</date>
    <language>und-Telu</language>
    <unicode-version>11.0.0</unicode-version>
    <description type="text/html"><![CDATA[
    <h1>Reference Label Generation Rules for the Telugu Script</h1>
    
    <h2>Overview</h2>
    <p>This document specifies a reference set of Label Generation Rules (LGR) for the Telugu script for the second level.
    The starting point for the development of this LGR can be found in the related Root Zone LGR [RZ-LGR-Telu]. 
    The format of this file follows [RFC 7940].</p>

    <p>For details and additional background on the script, see “Proposal for a Telugu Script Root Zone Label Generation Ruleset (LGR)” [Proposal-Telugu].</p>

<p class="notice">This document is a Review Draft and not final. Any version numbers shown are those of a possible future release. However, the draft may undergo significant revisions before any publication, or may be withdrawn.</p>

<h2>Repertoire</h2>
    <p>The repertoire contains 63 code points for letters catering to the Telugu language written using the Telugu script. Several other languages 
     with [EGIDS] levels above 4 were also considered in the analysis. The repertoire is a subset of [Unicode 11.0]. 
     For more detail, see Section 5, “Repertoire” in [Proposal-Telugu]. 
     (The proposal cited has been adopted for the Telugu script portion of the Root Zone LGR.)</p>

    <p>For the second level, the repertoire has been augmented with the ASCII digits, U+0030 to U+0039, and U+002D HYPHEN-MINUS, 
    for a total of 74 repertoire elements.</p>

    <p>Code points outside the Telugu script that are listed in this file are targets
      for out-of-script variants and are identified by a reflexive (identity)
      variant of type “out-of-repertoire-var”. They do not form part of the
      repertoire.</p>
      
    <p><b>Repertoire Listing:</b> Each code point or range is tagged with the script or scripts with which the code point is used,
    one or more tag values denoting character category, 
    and one or more references documenting sufficient justification for inclusion in the repertoire, see “References” below.
      Comments provide alternate names for some code points.</p>

     <h2>Variants</h2>
     <p>This reference LGR is designed for use in zones shared by more than one script.
     Where appropriate, cross-script variants have been defined to mutually exclude labels
     from different scripts that could otherwise be substituted by the users. Once a label
     has been delegated for one script, any of its variant labels consisting entirely of cross-script variants would be
     blocked. Any label containing at least one code point that is not a cross-script variant
     would be considered distinct. Because of that, even large numbers of defined cross-script
     variants generally do not lead to a high percentage of labels experiencing a collision.</p>

    <p>The Telugu and Kannada scripts are closely related to each other and there are many
    code points in both scripts which  can be confused with code points in the other script.
    This LGR defines many cross-script variants with Kannada. There are no in-script variants defined for Telugu. 
    For details, see Section 6, “Variants” in [Proposal-Telugu].</p>
    
    <p><b>Digit Variants:</b> The Telugu reference LGR does not include native digits, so there are no semantic variants defined.</p>

    <p>There are some homoglyph relations between Kannada and Telugu native digits,
    however, as the Telugu reference LGR does not support native digits, these do not give rise to variants.</p>
    By transitivity, all ASCII digits are semantic variants of any cross-script native digits.</p>
    <p>Any Telugu label that is otherwise a cross-script variant of a label in another script, will remain a variant
    if both labels add digits of the same value in the same position, irrespective of whether they are
    ASCII digits or (in the case of the other script) native digits. </p>

    <p>If native digits were supported instead of common digits, they would require variants to corresponding Kannada digits.</p>

    <p><b>Variant Disposition:</b> All variants are of type “blocked”, making labels that 
    differ only by these variants mutually exclusive: whichever label containing either of 
    these variants is chosen earlier would be delegated, while any other equivalent labels should be blocked.
    There is no preference among these labels.</p>

    <p>This LGR does not define allocatable variants.</p>
    
    <p>The specification of variants in this reference LGR follows the guidelines in [RFC 8228].</p>
      
    <h2>Character Classes</h2>
    <p>The Telugu orthography superficially resembles a series of circles and semi-circles. 
    Most consonants carry a tick mark called ‘talakattu’. The writing system is classified 
    as abugida type or alphasyllabary. The alphabet consists of vowels, 
    consonants and modifiers. Each of these vowels and consonants has one or more secondary 
    allographs.</p>

   <p><b>Consonants:</b> The Telugu consonants contain an implicit vowel  /a/.
     More details in Section 3.5.4, “The Consonants” in [Proposal-Telugu].</p>
     
    <p><b>Vowels and dependent vowel signs:</b> There are fourteen vowel characters in the common inventory of which 
    one is rarely used: U+0C0C. It and the two obsolete vowels, U+0C60 and U+0C61, are excluded from this LGR.
    Each vowel, except U+0C05 has a dependent vowel sign, modifying the vowel of the consonant they follow. 
    These signs may have different appearance depending on the size and 
    shape of the consonant that functions as an anchor. More details in Section 
    3.5.1, “The vowels and vowel modifiers” in [Proposal-Telugu]. </p>

    <p><b>Anusvara or sunna:</b> The Anusvara or sunna represents a homorganic nasal before the 
    corresponding consonant and as a substitute to transcribe word final /mu/. Essentially, 
    it substitutes a cluster of a Nasal Consonant+Halant before a consonant. More details 
    in Section 3.5.2, “The Anusvara or sunna” in [Proposal-Telugu].</p>
    
     <p><b>Visarga:</b>  Visarga denotes the glottal check.</p>
    
     <p><b>Halant:</b> A special sign is needed whenever the implicit vowel in the preceding 
     consonant is stripped off. This symbol is known as the Halant. (Any vowel sign will also override
     the implicit vowel). More 
    details in Section 3.5.1, “The vowels and vowel modifiers” in [Proposal-Telugu].</p>
      
    <h2>Whole Label Evaluation (WLE) and Context Rules</h2>
    <h3>Common Rules</h3>
        <ul>
          <li><b>Hyphen Restrictions</b> &mdash; restrictions on the allowable placement of hyphens (no leading/ending hyphen
             and no hyphen in positions 3 and 4). These restrictions are described in Section 4.2.3.1 of RFC 5891 [150]. 
             They are implemented here as context rule on U+002D (-) HYPHEN-MINUS.</li>
          <li><b>Leading Combining Marks</b>   &mdash;  restrictions on the allowable placement of combining marks
             (no leading combining mark). This rule is described in Section 4.2.3.2 of RFC 5891 [150].</li>
    </ul>
    <h3>Default Actions</h3>
    <p>This LGR includes the default actions for LGRs as well as the action needed to
        invalidate labels with misplaced combining marks. They are marked with &#x235F;.
        For a description see [RFC 7940].</p> 
        
    <h3>Telugu-specific Rules</h3>
    <p>These rules have been formulated so that they can be adopted for  LGR specification.</p>
    <p>The following symbols are used in the WLE rules: 
    <br/>C    →    Consonant
    <br/>M     →    Matra (Dependent vowel signs)
    <br/>V    →    Vowel
    <br/>B    →    Anusvara (Bindu)  
    <br/>X    →    Visarga        
    <br/>H    →    Halant / Virama
    </p>
    
    <p>The rules are: </p>
     <ul>
     <li>1. H: must be preceded by C</li>
     <li>2. M: must be preceded by C</li>
     <li>3. X: must be preceded by V, M or C</li>
     <li>4. B: must be preceded by V, M or C</li>
     <li>6. V: cannot be preceded by H</li>
     </ul>
    
     <p>More details in Section 7, “Whole Label Evaluation Rules (WLE)” in [Proposal-Telugu]. The numbering of the rules given here, follows that document.</p>
    
    <h2>Methodology and Contributors</h2>
    <p>This reference LGR for the Telugu script for the second level has been developed by Michel Suignard and Asmus Freytag, based on the Root Zone LGR for the Telugu 
    script and information contained or referenced therein, see [RZ-LGR-Telu]. Suitable extensions for the second level have been applied according to the [Guidelines] and with community input. 
    The original proposal for a Root Zone LGR for the Telugu script, that this reference LGR is based on, was developed by the Neo-Brahmi Generation Panel (NBGP). 
    For more information on methodology and contributors to the underlying Root Zone LGR, see Sections 4 and 8 in [Proposal-Telugu], as well as [RZ-LGR-Overview].</p>

    <h3>Changes from Version 1</h3> <p>Unicode Version has been updated.</p>
    <h2>References</h2> 
    <p>The following general references are cited in this document:</p>
    <dl class="references">

    <dt>[Guidelines]</dt>
    <dd>ICANN, “Guidelines for Developing Reference LGRs for the Second Level”, (Los Angeles, California: ICANN, 27 May 2020), https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/lgr-guidelines-second-level-27may20-en.pdf</dd> 

     <dt>[EGIDS]</dt>
     <dd>Expanded Graded Intergenerational Disruption Scale, https://www.ethnologue.com/about/language-status (Accessed on 13 Nov. 2017)</dd>

    <dt>[Proposal-Telugu]</dt>
     <dd>Neo-Brahmi Generation Panel, “Proposal for a Telugu Script Root Zone Label Generation Ruleset (LGR)”, 7 June 2019, https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/proposal-telugu-lgr-07Jun19-en.pdf</dd>

    <dt>[RFC 7940]</dt>
     <dd>Davies, K. and A. Freytag, “Representing Label Generation Rulesets Using XML”, RFC 7940, August 2016, https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7940</dd> 

    <dt>[RFC 8228]</dt>
    <dd>A. Freytag, “Guidance on Designing Label Generation Rulesets (LGRs) Supporting Variant Labels”, RFC 8228, August 2017,
    https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8228</dd>

     <dt>[RZ-LGR-Overview]</dt>
    <dd>Integration Panel, “Root Zone Label Generation Rules - LGR-5: Overview and Summary”, 26 May 2022 (PDF), https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/rz-lgr-5-overview-26may22-en.pdf</dd>

     <dt>[RZ-LGR-Telu]</dt>
     <dd>ICANN, Root Zone Label Generation Rules for the Telugu Script (und-Telu) , 26 May 2022 (XML)
https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/rz-lgr-5-telugu-script-26may22-en.xml</dd>

     <dt>[Unicode 11.0]</dt>
     <dd>The Unicode Consortium. The Unicode Standard, Version 11.0.0, (Mountain View, CA: The Unicode Consortium, 2018. ISBN 978-1-936213-19-1) 
     https://www.unicode.org/versions/Unicode11.0.0/</dd>
     </dl>
      <p>For references consulted particularly in designing the repertoire for the Telugu script for the second level 
      please see details in the <a href="#table_of_references">Table of References</a> below. 
      Reference [0]   refers to the Unicode Standard version in which the
      corresponding code points were initially encoded. References [102] and above correspond to sources
      given in [Proposal-Telugu] justifying the inclusion of the corresponding code points. Entries in the table may have
      multiple source reference values. Reference [150] indicates the source for common rules.</p>

]]></description>
    <references>
      <reference id="0" comment="Any code point originally encoded in Unicode 1.1">The Unicode Standard 1.1</reference>
      <reference id="102">Krishnamurti, Bhadriraju (Ed.). 2000. Telugu bhaashaa charitra. Hyderabad: P.S. Telugu University. (first edition 1974)</reference>
      <reference id="103">Krishnamurti, Bhadriraju and J P L Gwynn. 1985.  A Grammar of Modern Telugu. New Delhi: Oxford University Press. ISBN 978-0-19-561664-4</reference>
      <reference id="150">RFC 5891, Internationalized Domain Names in Applications (IDNA): Protocol https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5891</reference>
    </references>
  </meta>
  <data>
    <char cp="002D" not-when="hyphen-minus-disallowed" tag="sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="HYPHEN-MINUS; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0030" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT ZERO; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0031" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT ONE; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0032" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT TWO; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0033" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT THREE; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0034" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT FOUR; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0035" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT FIVE; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0036" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT SIX; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0037" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT SEVEN; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0038" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT EIGHT; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0039" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT NINE; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0C02" when="follows-V-M-or-C" tag="Anusvara sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" comment="= sunna">
      <var cp="0C82" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C03" when="follows-V-M-or-C" tag="sc:Telu Visarga" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0C83" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C05" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Telu Vowel" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0C85" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C06" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Telu Vowel" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0C86" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C07" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Telu Vowel" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0C87" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C08" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Telu Vowel" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0C88" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C09" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Telu Vowel" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C0A" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Telu Vowel" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C0B" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Telu Vowel" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C0E" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Telu Vowel" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C0F" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Telu Vowel" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C10" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Telu Vowel" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0C90" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C12" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Telu Vowel" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0C92" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C13" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Telu Vowel" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0C93" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C14" not-when="follows-H" tag="sc:Telu Vowel" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0C94" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C15" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C16" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0C96" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C17" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0C97" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C18" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C19" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C1A" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C1B" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C1C" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0C9C" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C1D" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0C9D" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C1E" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0C9E" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C1F" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0C9F" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C20" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CA0" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C21" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CA1" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C22" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CA2" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C23" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CA3" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C24" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C25" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CA5" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C26" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CA6" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C27" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CA7" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C28" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CA8" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C2A" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C2B" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C2C" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CAC" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C2D" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CAD" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C2E" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CAE" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C2F" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CAF" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C30" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CB0" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C32" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CB2" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C33" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CB3" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C35" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C36" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C37" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C38" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C39" tag="Consonant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C3E" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C3F" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CBF" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C40" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C41" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CC1" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C42" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C43" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103">
      <var cp="0CC3" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C44" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C46" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C47" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C48" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C4A" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C4B" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C4C" when="follows-C" tag="Matra sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" />
    <char cp="0C4D" when="follows-C" tag="Halant sc:Telu" ref="0 102 103" comment="= halant" />
    <char cp="0C82" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C02" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0C82" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C83" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C03" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0C83" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C85" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C05" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0C85" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C86" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C06" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0C86" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C87" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C07" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0C87" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C88" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C08" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0C88" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C90" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C10" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0C90" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C92" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C12" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0C92" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C93" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C13" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0C93" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C94" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C14" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0C94" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C96" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C16" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0C96" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C97" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C17" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0C97" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C9C" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C1C" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0C9C" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C9D" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C1D" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0C9D" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C9E" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C1E" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0C9E" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0C9F" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C1F" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0C9F" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CA0" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C20" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CA0" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CA1" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C21" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CA1" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CA2" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C22" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CA2" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CA3" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C23" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CA3" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CA5" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C25" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CA5" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CA6" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C26" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CA6" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CA7" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C27" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CA7" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CA8" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C28" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CA8" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CAC" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C2C" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CAC" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CAD" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C2D" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CAD" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CAE" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C2E" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CAE" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CAF" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C2F" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CAF" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CB0" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C30" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CB0" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CB2" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C32" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CB2" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CB3" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C33" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CB3" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CBF" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C3F" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CBF" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CC1" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C41" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CC1" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0CC3" tag="sc:Knda" ref="0" comment="Not part of repertoire">
      <var cp="0C43" type="blocked" comment="Cross-script homoglyph" />
      <var cp="0CC3" type="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="Out-of-repertoire" />
    </char>
  </data>
  <!--Rules section goes here-->
  <rules>
    <!--Character class definitions go here-->
    <class name="C" from-tag="Consonant" comment="Any Telugu consonant" />
    <class name="V" from-tag="Vowel" comment="Any Telugu independent vowel" />
    <class name="M" from-tag="Matra" comment="Any Telugu vowel sign (matra)" />
    <class name="H" from-tag="Halant" comment="The Telugu Halant / Virama" />
    <!--Whole label evaluation and context rules go here-->
    <rule name="leading-combining-mark" ref="150" comment="RFC 5891 restrictions on placement of combining marks &#x235F;">
      <start />
      <union>
        <class property="gc:Mn" />
        <class property="gc:Mc" />
      </union>
    </rule>
    <rule name="hyphen-minus-disallowed" ref="150" comment="RFC 5891 restrictions on placement of U+002D &#x235F;">
      <choice>
        <rule comment="no leading hyphen">
          <look-behind>
            <start />
          </look-behind>
          <anchor />
        </rule>
        <rule comment="no trailing hyphen">
          <anchor />
          <look-ahead>
            <end />
          </look-ahead>
        </rule>
        <rule comment="no consecutive hyphens in third and fourth position in the label">
          <look-behind>
            <start />
            <any />
            <any />
            <char cp="002D" comment="hyphen-minus" />
          </look-behind>
          <anchor />
        </rule>
      </choice>
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-C" comment="Section 7, WLE 1: H must be preceded by a C; WLE 2: M must be preceded by C">
      <look-behind>
        <class by-ref="C" />
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-V-M-or-C" comment="Section 7, WLE 3: Visarga must be preceded by V, M or C; WLE 4: Anusvara must be preceded by V, M or C">
      <look-behind>
        <choice>
          <class by-ref="V" />
          <class by-ref="M" />
          <class by-ref="C" />
        </choice>
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-H" comment="Section 7, WLE 6: V cannot be preceded by H">
      <look-behind>
        <class by-ref="H" />
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <!--Action elements go here - order defines precedence-->
    <action disp="invalid" match="leading-combining-mark" ref="150" comment="labels with leading combining marks are invalid &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="invalid" any-variant="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="any variant label with a code point out of repertoire is invalid &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="blocked" any-variant="blocked" comment="any variant label containing blocked variants is blocked &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="allocatable" all-variants="allocatable" comment="variant labels with all variants allocatable are allocatable &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="valid" comment="catch all (default action) &#x235F;" />
  </rules>
</lgr>