<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<lgr xmlns="urn:ietf:params:xml:ns:lgr-1.0">
  <meta>
    <version comment="Second Level Reference LGR">2</version>
    <date>2022-05-31</date>
    <language>und-Sinh</language>
    <unicode-version>11.0.0</unicode-version>
    <description type="text/html"><![CDATA[
    <h1>Reference Label Generation Rules for the Sinhala Script</h1>
    
  <h2>Overview</h2>
    <p>This document specifies a reference set of Label Generation Rules (LGR) for the Sinhala script for the second level. 
     The starting point for the development of this LGR can be found in the related Root Zone LGR [RZ-LGR-Sinh]. 
     The format of this file follows [RFC 7940].</p> 

     <p>For details and additional background on the script, see “Proposal for a 
    Sinhala Script Root Zone Label Generation Rules-Set  (LGR)" [Proposal-Sinhala].</p>

<p class="notice">This document is a Review Draft and not final. Any version numbers shown are those of a possible future release. However, the draft may undergo significant revisions before any publication, or may be withdrawn.</p>

 <h2>Repertoire</h2>
    <p>The repertoire covers the Sinhala language as written with the Sinhala script and contains 72 code points for letters.  
    In addition, 4 sequences are used in the definition of variants. The repertoire is a subset of [Unicode 11.0].
    For more detail, see Section 5, “Repertoire” in [Proposal-Sinhala]. 
    (The proposal cited has been adopted for the Sinhala script portion of the Root Zone LGR.)</p>

    <p>For the second level, the repertoire has been augmented with the ASCII digits, U+0030 to U+0039, and U+002D HYPHEN-MINUS,
    and the number of sequences increased to 112 by adding common sequences using ZWJ (U+200D), including some with variants,
    for a total of 195 repertoire elements. In addition to ZWJ, the letter U+0DA6 SINHALA LETTER SANYAKA JAYANNA
    is  defined only in the context of an enumerated sequence.</p>

     <p><b>Repertoire Listing:</b> Each code point or range is tagged with the script or scripts with which the code point is used, 
     one or more tag values denoting character category, 
     and one or more references documenting sufficient justification for inclusion in the repertoire, see “References” below.</p>

     <h2>Variants</h2>
     <p>This reference LGR is designed for use in zones shared by more than one script.
     Where appropriate, cross-script variants have been defined to mutually exclude labels
     from different scripts that could otherwise be substituted by the users. Once a label
     has been delegated for one script, any of its variant labels consisting entirely of cross-script variants would be
     blocked. Any label containing at least one code point that is not a cross-script variant
     would be considered distinct. Because of that, even large numbers of defined cross-script
     variants generally do not lead to a high percentage of labels experiencing a collision.</p>

    <p>This LGR defines variants within Sinhala as described in Section 6, “Variants”, in “[Proposal-Sinhala]”. Additionally,
    some of the common conjuncts have alternates which are treated as variants.</p>

    <p><b>Digit Variants:</b> The Sinhala reference LGR does not include native digits, so there are no semantic variants defined.</p>

    <p><b>Variant Disposition:</b> All variants are of type “blocked”, making labels that 
    differ only by these variants mutually exclusive: whichever label containing either of 
    these variants is chosen earlier would be delegated, while any other equivalent labels should be blocked.
    There is no preference among these labels.</p>

  <p>This LGR does not define allocatable variants.</p>
  
    <p>The specification of variants in this reference LGR follows the guidelines in [RFC 8228].</p>

    <p><b>Context Rules for Variants:</b> for some of the variants defined in this LGR 
     the sequences or code points making up source and target are constrained by explicit
    context rules on the code points (or by implicit context rules defined for the adjacent code points). 
     In such a case, any variants may require context rules that match the intersection
    between the effective contexts for both source and target; otherwise, a sequence might be considered valid in some
    variant label when it would not be valid in an equivalent context in an original label. Symmetry requires
    the same context rule for both forward and reverse mappings.</p>

  <h2>Character Classes</h2>
  <p>As most Brahmi-derived scripts, Sinhala is an alphasyllabary writing system and written from 
  left to right. All the categories of Consonants, Vowels, Matras, Halant, Anusvara, Visarga and Sannjakas are discussed below. </p>

  <p><b>Consonants:</b> There are 40 consonants in Sinhala alphabet and 38 of them are selected for inclusion. 
  Its consonants imply inherent vowel a(අ) when they are used without dependent vowels. Absence of the 
  inherent vowel is marked by adding hal kirima (remover of the inherent vowel) to the consonant; thus ක 
  /ka/ but ක් /k/, and ව /va/ but ව් /v/. More details in Section 3.3.1, “The Consonants” in [Proposal-Sinhala].</p>
  
  <p><b>Vowels and Matras:</b> There are separate symbols (dependent vowels) for all the vowels except the inherent 
  vowel අ in Sinhala. Independent vowels are used at the beginning of a word and dependent vowels (matras) are used after 
  consonants.  More details in Section 3.3.2, “The Vowels” in [Proposal-Sinhala]. </p>

  <p><b>Halanta:</b>  The Halanta, which is also called halkirima or hallakuna, is encoded as U+0DCA ( &#x0DCA; ) SINHALA SIGN AL-LAKUNA.  
  This sign is used to remove the 
  inherent vowel of the consonants in Sinhala, and to join consonants and form conjunct 
  characters. More details in Section 3.3.3, “Halanta: The Inherent Vowel Remover” in [Proposal-Sinhala]. </p>

  <p><b>Anusvara:</b> U+0D82 ( ං ) SINHALA SIGN ANUSVARAYA, pronounced /ŋ/, represents all the 
  nasals. It can be preceded by any sign except halanta (U+0DCA). More details 
  in Section 3.3.4, “The Anusvara” in [Proposal-Sinhala]. </p>
  
  <p><b>Visarga:</b> U+0D83 ( ඃ ) SINHALA SIGN VISARGAYA is a rarely used sign and pronounced as /h/. It can be
   preceded by any sign except halanta (U+0DCA). More details in 
   Section 3.3.5, “The Visarga” in [Proposal-Sinhala]. </p>

  <p><b>Sannjakas:</b> There are five separate letters for prenasalized voiced stops called sannjakas in 
  Sinhala. From among these, ඦ is not frequently used. Sannjakas cannot 
  be followed by halanta. More details in Section 3.3.6, “Sannjakas” in [Proposal-Sinhala]. </p>

  <p><b>Zero Width Joiner:</b> This character is used in the formation of certain conjuncts in Sinhala.
  In this LGR, U+200D (ZWJ) is not listed by itself but available as part of many defined sequences.</p>
      
    <h2>Whole Label Evaluation (WLE) and Context Rules</h2>
  <h3>Common Rules</h3>
        <ul>
          <li><b>Hyphen Restrictions</b> &mdash; restrictions on the allowable placement of hyphens (no leading/ending hyphen
             and no hyphen in positions 3 and 4). These restrictions are described in Section 4.2.3.1 of RFC 5891 [150]. 
             They are implemented here as context rule on U+002D (-) HYPHEN-MINUS.</li>
          <li><b>Leading Combining Marks</b>   &mdash;  restrictions on the allowable placement of combining marks
             (no leading combining mark). This rule is described in Section 4.2.3.2 of RFC 5891 [150].</li>
    </ul>
  <h3>Default Actions</h3>
  <p>This LGR includes the default actions for LGRs as well as the action needed to
        invalidate labels with misplaced combining marks. They are marked with &#x235F;.
        For a description see [RFC 7940].</p> 
    
  <h3>Sinhala-specific Rules</h3>
  <p>These rules have been formulated so that they can be adopted for  LGR specification.</p>
  <p>The following symbols are used in the WLE rules: 
  <br/>C  → Consonant
  <br/>M  → Matra / Vowel Signs
  <br/>V  → Vowel
  <br/>B  → Anusvara (Bindu) 
  <br/>X  → Visarga
  <br/>H  → Halanta / Virama   
  <br/>J  → Sannjaka
  </p>
  
  <p>The rules are: </p>
   <ul>
   <li>1. H: must be preceded by C</li>
   <li>2. M: must be preceded by C or J</li>
   <li>3. X: must be preceded by either V, C, or M </li>
   <li>4. B: must be preceded by either V, C, J or M</li>
   <li>5. H: must not follow conjunct sequence</li>
   </ul>

    <p>The following context rules apply to code points in variant sets to ensure the variant transitivity.</p>
    <ul>
    <li>5. variants are undefined preceding a Halant or Matra</li>
    <li>6. variants are undefined preceding an Anusvara, Visarga, Halant or Matra</li>
    </ul>
  
   <p>More details in Section 7, “Whole Label Evaluation Rules (WLE)” in [Proposal-Sinhala].</p>
  
  <h2>Methodology and Contributors</h2>
  <p>This reference LGR for the Sinhala script for the second level has been developed by Michel Suignard and Asmus Freytag, based on the Root Zone LGR for the Sinhala 
  script and information contained or referenced therein, see [RZ-LGR-Sinh]. Suitable extensions for the second level have been applied according to the [Guidelines] and with community input. 
  The original proposal for a Root Zone LGR for the Sinhala script, that this reference LGR is based on, was developed by the Sinhala Generation Panel in consultation with the Neo-Brahmi Generation Panel.
  For more information on methodology and contributors to the underlying Root Zone LGR, see Sections 4 and 8 in [Proposal-Sinhala], as well as [RZ-LGR-Overview].</p>
    <h3>Changes from Version 1</h3> <p>Unicode Version has been updated.</p>

    <h2>References</h2> 
  <p>The following general references are cited in this document:</p>
  <dl class="references">
    <dt>[Guidelines]</dt>
    <dd>ICANN, “Guidelines for Developing Reference LGRs for the Second Level”, (Los Angeles, California: ICANN, 27 May 2020), https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/lgr-guidelines-second-level-27may20-en.pdf</dd>

  <dt>[Proposal-Sinhala]</dt> <dd>Sinhala Generation Panel, “Proposal for a Sinhala Script Root Zone Label Generation Ruleset (LGR)”, 22 April 2019, https://www.icann.org/en/system/files/files/proposal-sinhala-lgr-22apr19-en.pdf</dd>

  <dt>[RFC 7940]</dt>
   <dd>Davies, K. and A. Freytag, “Representing Label Generation Rulesets Using XML”, RFC 7940, August 2016, https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7940</dd> 
   
    <dt>[RFC 8228]</dt>
    <dd>A. Freytag, “Guidance on Designing Label Generation Rulesets (LGRs) Supporting Variant Labels”, RFC 8228, August 2017,
    https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8228</dd>
      <dt>[RZ-LGR-Overview]</dt>
       <dd>Integration Panel, “Root Zone Label Generation Rules - LGR-5: Overview and Summary”, 26 May 2022 (PDF), https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/rz-lgr-5-overview-26may22-en.pdf</dd>

     <dt>[RZ-LGR-Sinh]</dt>
     <dd>ICANN, Root Zone Label Generation Rules for the Sinhala Script (und-Sinh) , 26 May 2022 (XML)
https://www.icann.org/sites/default/files/lgr/rz-lgr-5-sinhala-script-26may22-en.xml</dd>
     <dt>[Unicode 11.0]</dt>
   <dd>The Unicode Consortium. The Unicode Standard, Version 11.0.0, (Mountain View, CA: The Unicode Consortium, 2018. ISBN 978-1-936213-19-1) 
   https://www.unicode.org/versions/Unicode11.0.0/</dd>
   </dl>
      <p>For references consulted particularly in designing the repertoire for the Sinhala script for the second level 
      please see details in the <a href="#table_of_references">Table of References</a> below. 
      Reference [0] refers to the Unicode Standard version in which the
      corresponding code points were initially encoded. References [102] and above correspond to sources
      given in [Proposal-Sinhala] justifying the inclusion of the corresponding code points. Entries in the table may have
      multiple source reference values. Reference [150] indicates the source for common rules.</p>

]]></description>
    <references>
      <reference id="0" comment="Any code point originally encoded in Unicode 1.1">The Unicode Standard 1.1</reference>
      <reference id="102">Disanayaka, JB. 2006. Sinhala Akshara Vicharaya (Sinhala Graphology), Sumitha Publishers, Kalubovila. ISBN: 955-1146-44-1</reference>
      <reference id="103">Sections 5.8 through 5.10, and 6.4 “Conjunct Letters” in SRI LANKA STANDARD 1134 : 2011  https://www.language.lk/wp-content/uploads/2018/03/SLS-1134-2011.pdf [language.lk]</reference>
      <reference id="201">Omniglot: The on-line encyclopedia of writing system and Languages, “Sinhala”  https://www.omniglot.com/writing/sinhala.htm</reference>
      <reference id="150">RFC 5891, Internationalized Domain Names in Applications (IDNA): Protocol https://tools.ietf.org/html/rfc5891</reference>
      <reference id="3" comment="Any code point originally encoded in Unicode 3.0">The Unicode Standard 3.0</reference>
    </references>
  </meta>
  <data>
    <char cp="002D" not-when="hyphen-minus-disallowed" tag="sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="HYPHEN-MINUS; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0030" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT ZERO; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0031" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT ONE; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0032" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT TWO; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0033" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT THREE; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0034" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT FOUR; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0035" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT FIVE; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0036" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT SIX; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0037" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT SEVEN; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0038" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT EIGHT; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0039" tag="Common-digit sc:Zyyy" ref="0" comment="DIGIT NINE; &#x235F;" />
    <char cp="0D82" when="follows-V-C-J-or-M" tag="Anusvara sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0D83" when="follows-V-C-or-M" tag="sc:Sinh Visarga" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0D85" tag="sc:Sinh Vowel" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0D86" tag="sc:Sinh Vowel" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0D87" tag="sc:Sinh Vowel" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0D88" tag="sc:Sinh Vowel" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0D89" tag="sc:Sinh Vowel" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0D8A" tag="sc:Sinh Vowel" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0D8B" tag="sc:Sinh Vowel" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0D8C" tag="sc:Sinh Vowel" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0D8D" tag="sc:Sinh Vowel" ref="3 102 201">
      <var cp="0D9D 0DD8" not-when="followed-by-H-or-M" type="blocked" />
      <var cp="0DC3 0DD8" not-when="followed-by-H-or-M" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D91" tag="sc:Sinh Vowel" ref="3 102 201">
      <var cp="0DB5" not-when="followed-by-H-or-M" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D92" tag="sc:Sinh Vowel" ref="3 102 201">
      <var cp="0DB5 0DCA" not-when="followed-by-B-X-H-or-M" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D93" tag="sc:Sinh Vowel" ref="3 102 201">
      <var cp="0DB5 0DD9" not-when="followed-by-H-or-M" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D94" tag="sc:Sinh Vowel" ref="3 102 201">
      <var cp="0DB9" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D95" tag="sc:Sinh Vowel" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0D96" tag="sc:Sinh Vowel" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0D9A" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0D9A 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0D9A 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0D9A 0DCA 200D 0DC2" ref="103" comment="Commonly used conjunct" />
    <char cp="0D9B" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201">
      <var cp="0DB6" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D9B 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0D9B 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0D9C" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0D9C 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0D9C 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0D9D" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201">
      <var cp="0DC3" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D9D 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0D9D 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0D9D 0DD8" ref="102 201" comment="variant of IRUYANNA">
      <var cp="0D8D" not-when="followed-by-H-or-M" type="blocked" />
      <var cp="0DC3 0DD8" not-when="followed-by-H-or-M" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0D9F" tag="Sannjaka sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DA0" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201">
      <var cp="0DC0" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0DA0 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA0 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA1" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DA1 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA1 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA2" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DA2 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA2 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA3" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DA3 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA3 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA4" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DA4 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA4 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA5" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DA5 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA5 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA7" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DA7 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA7 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA8" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DA8 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA8 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA9" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DA9 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DA9 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DAA" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DAA 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DAA 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DAB" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DAB 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DAB 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DAC" tag="Sannjaka sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DAD" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DAD 0DCA 200D 0DAE" ref="103" comment="Commonly used conjunct" />
    <char cp="0DAD 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DAD 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DAE" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DAE 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DAE 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DAF" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DAF 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DAF 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DB0" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DB0 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DB0 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DB1" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DB1 0DCA 200D 0DAE" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Commonly used conjunct" />
    <char cp="0DB1 0DCA 200D 0DAF" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Commonly used conjunct" />
    <char cp="0DB1 0DCA 200D 0DB0" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Commonly used conjunct" />
    <char cp="0DB1 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DB1 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DB3" tag="Sannjaka sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DB4" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DB4 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DB4 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DB5" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201">
      <var cp="0D91" not-when="followed-by-H-or-M" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0DB5 0DCA" ref="102 201" comment="variant of  EEYANNA">
      <var cp="0D92" not-when="followed-by-B-X-H-or-M" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0DB5 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DB5 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DB5 0DD9" ref="102 201" comment="variant of AIYANNA">
      <var cp="0D93" not-when="followed-by-H-or-M" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0DB6" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201">
      <var cp="0D9B" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0DB6 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DB6 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DB7" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201">
      <var cp="0DC4" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0DB7 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DB7 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DB8" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DB8 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DB8 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DB9" tag="Sannjaka sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201">
      <var cp="0D94" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0DBA" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DBA 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBA 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0D9A" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0D9B" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0D9C" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0D9D" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DA0" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DA1" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DA2" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DA3" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DA4" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DA5" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DA6" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DA7" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DA8" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DA9" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DAA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DAB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DAD" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DAE" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DAF" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DB0" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DB1" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DB4" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DB5" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DB6" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DB7" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DB8" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA">
      <var cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DBA 0DCA 200D 0DBA" type="blocked" comment="Common alternate" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DBA 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Conjunct">
      <var cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DBA" type="blocked" comment="Common alternate" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DBD" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DC0" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DC1" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DC2" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DC3" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DC4" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DC5" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBB 0DCA 200D 0DC6" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with REPAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBD" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DBD 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DBD 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DC0" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201">
      <var cp="0DA0" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0DC0 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DC0 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DC1" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DC1 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DC1 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DC2" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DC2 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DC2 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DC3" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201">
      <var cp="0D9D" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0DC3 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DC3 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DC3 0DD8" ref="102 201" comment="variant of IRUYANNA">
      <var cp="0D8D" not-when="followed-by-H-or-M" type="blocked" />
      <var cp="0D9D 0DD8" not-when="followed-by-H-or-M" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0DC4" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201">
      <var cp="0DB7" type="blocked" />
    </char>
    <char cp="0DC4 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DC4 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DC5" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DC5 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DC6" tag="Consonant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DC6 0DCA 200D 0DBA" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with YANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DC6 0DCA 200D 0DBB" not-when="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="Letter with RAKARANSAYA" />
    <char cp="0DCA" when="follows-C" tag="Halant sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DCF" when="follows-C-or-J" tag="Matra sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DD0" when="follows-C-or-J" tag="Matra sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DD1" when="follows-C-or-J" tag="Matra sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DD2" when="follows-C-or-J" tag="Matra sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DD3" when="follows-C-or-J" tag="Matra sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DD4" when="follows-C-or-J" tag="Matra sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DD6" when="follows-C-or-J" tag="Matra sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DD8" when="follows-C-or-J" tag="Matra sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DD9" when="follows-C-or-J" tag="Matra sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DDA" when="follows-C-or-J" tag="Matra sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DDB" when="follows-C-or-J" tag="Matra sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DDC" when="follows-C-or-J" tag="Matra sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DDD" when="follows-C-or-J" tag="Matra sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DDE" when="follows-C-or-J" tag="Matra sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
    <char cp="0DF2" when="follows-C-or-J" tag="Matra sc:Sinh" ref="3 102 201" />
  </data>
  <!--Rules section goes here-->
  <rules>
    <!--Character class definitions go here-->
    <class name="C" from-tag="Consonant" comment="Any Sinhala consonant" />
    <class name="V" from-tag="Vowel" comment="Any Sinhala independent vowel" />
    <class name="M" from-tag="Matra" comment="Any Sinhala vowel sign (matra)" />
    <class name="J" from-tag="Sannjaka" comment="Any Sinhala Sannjaka" />
    <class name="H" from-tag="Halant" comment="The Sinhala Al-Lakuna (Halant)" />
    <class name="B" from-tag="Anusvara" comment="The Sinhala Anusvara" />
    <class name="X" from-tag="Visarga" comment="The Sinhala Visarga" />
    <!--Whole label evaluation and context rules go here-->
    <rule name="leading-combining-mark" ref="150" comment="RFC 5891 restrictions on placement of combining marks &#x235F;">
      <start />
      <union>
        <class property="gc:Mn" />
        <class property="gc:Mc" />
      </union>
    </rule>
    <rule name="hyphen-minus-disallowed" ref="150" comment="RFC 5891 restrictions on placement of U+002D &#x235F;">
      <choice>
        <rule comment="no leading hyphen">
          <look-behind>
            <start />
          </look-behind>
          <anchor />
        </rule>
        <rule comment="no trailing hyphen">
          <anchor />
          <look-ahead>
            <end />
          </look-ahead>
        </rule>
        <rule comment="no consecutive hyphens in third and fourth position in the label">
          <look-behind>
            <start />
            <any />
            <any />
            <char cp="002D" comment="hyphen-minus" />
          </look-behind>
          <anchor />
        </rule>
      </choice>
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-C" comment="Section 7, WLE 1: Halanta/Virama must be preceded by C">
      <look-behind>
        <class by-ref="C" />
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-C-or-J" comment="Section 7, WLE 2: Matra must be preceded by C or J">
      <look-behind>
        <choice>
          <class by-ref="C" />
          <class by-ref="J" />
        </choice>
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-V-C-or-M" comment="Section 7, WLE 3: Visarga must be preceded by V, C or M">
      <look-behind>
        <choice>
          <class by-ref="V" />
          <class by-ref="C" />
          <class by-ref="M" />
        </choice>
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="follows-V-C-J-or-M" comment="Section 7, WLE 4: Anusvara (Bindu) must be preceded by V, C, J or M">
      <look-behind>
        <choice>
          <class by-ref="V" />
          <class by-ref="C" />
          <class by-ref="J" />
          <class by-ref="M" />
        </choice>
      </look-behind>
      <anchor />
    </rule>
    <rule name="followed-by-H" ref="103" comment="sequences cannot be followed by a Halant">
      <anchor />
      <look-ahead>
        <class by-ref="H" />
      </look-ahead>
    </rule>
    <rule name="followed-by-H-or-M" comment="variants are undefined preceding a Halant or Matra">
      <anchor />
      <look-ahead>
        <choice>
          <class by-ref="H" />
          <class by-ref="M" />
        </choice>
      </look-ahead>
    </rule>
    <rule name="followed-by-B-X-H-or-M" comment="variants are undefined preceding an Anusvara, Visarga, Halant or Matra">
      <anchor />
      <look-ahead>
        <choice>
          <class by-ref="B" />
          <class by-ref="X" />
          <class by-ref="H" />
          <class by-ref="M" />
        </choice>
      </look-ahead>
    </rule>
    <!--Action elements go here - order defines precedence-->
    <action disp="invalid" match="leading-combining-mark" ref="150" comment="labels with leading combining marks are invalid &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="invalid" any-variant="out-of-repertoire-var" comment="any variant label with a code point out of repertoire is invalid &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="blocked" any-variant="blocked" comment="any variant label containing blocked variants is blocked &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="allocatable" all-variants="allocatable" comment="variant labels with all variants allocatable are allocatable &#x235F;" />
    <action disp="valid" comment="catch all (default action) &#x235F;" />
  </rules>
</lgr>